<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scarron incens'd, or, His appearing to Madam de Maintenon, his late wife, reproaching her amours with Lewis the Great, present King of France and discovering several secrets of that court / written by a lady in French.</title>
            <author>Lady.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12389072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12389072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62321)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 227:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scarron incens'd, or, His appearing to Madam de Maintenon, his late wife, reproaching her amours with Lewis the Great, present King of France and discovering several secrets of that court / written by a lady in French.</title>
                  <author>Lady.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 15-139, [5] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Randall Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: [1]-[5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scarron, --  Monsieur, 1610-1660 --  In literature.</term>
               <term>Maintenon, --  Madame de, 1635-1719 --  Fiction.</term>
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:60948:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. La Maintenon</item>
                        <item>2. Scarron</item>
                        <item>3. Ragotin</item>
                        <item>4. La Rancune</item>
                        <item>5. La Rapiniere</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>F. H. van. Hove. sculp:</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60948:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SCARRON</hi> INCENS'D: OR, His Appearing to Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> His late Wife, Reproaching her Amours with <hi>LEWIS the Great,</hi> Preſent King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And diſcovering ſeveral SECRETS of that COURT,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by a Lady in French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60948:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Make you this ſmall Preſent, not through any Inducements of Vanity, nor to ſet up for an Author not having the Honour to be known to ye. Your Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is my Deſign, and
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:3"/>to give you a faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome Particulars of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> always abounding in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Intrigues, which merit Attention, and the Pains of committing 'em to White Paper, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the moſt Polite Part of the World, and where all the Sweets of Life are taſted with the greateſt Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The Subject of my Story is a Real Adventure
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:3"/>that lately befell Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> as you will find by the Sequel. <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> appear'd to her with a penſive and louring Air, and upbraided her with the whole Conduct of her Life, but more-eſpecially with her Amorous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi> The Perſons I have made choice of to accompany his Ghoſt into this World, will make you believe, perhaps, the Story to be Fabulous; but my
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:4"/>dear Friend, let not that infuſe into yee any Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Incredulity. For I only mention the ſame Perſons which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Maintenon</hi> nam'd her ſelf, in recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of her Dreams to a Lady of my intimate Acquaintance, for whom ſhe has a paſſionate Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in whoſe Breaſt ſhe lodges all her Secrets, who was pleas'd to impart to me the knowledge of it in theſe Words, <hi>That
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:4"/>ſhe found her ſelf in a deep melancholy, for having ſeen and ſpoken to</hi> M. Scarron, <hi>who was attended by his Friends,</hi> La Rapiniere, La Rancune, <hi>and</hi> Ragou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</p>
            <p>You are not ignorant that theſe Illuſtrious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages were Famous <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's</hi> in the Romances of that Author, and that he mentions 'em every day, as well as our <hi>Heroeſs;</hi> for ſhe had alſo her impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:5"/>Shares in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime of the Court. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the Pilgrimages and Penances which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs has lately under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, may be look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as ſenſible Proofs of the Truth of her Viſion; thoſe Hardſhips being thought a ſort of Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms to ſend <hi>Scarron</hi> to a Place where he may be better employ'd then to take notice of his Wife's Behaviour in this World:
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:5"/>for 'tis thought he is ſtill in Purgatory, and is afraid his Wife will follow him thither. Which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the poor Lady is continually at her Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; eſpecially at St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> whither I have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour frequently to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany her, as being very much in her Favour.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reaſons why I durſt not give this Hiſtory to the Bookſellers in <hi>France,</hi>
               <pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:6"/>being aſſur'd that they would never have printed it, by reaſon of certain Paſſages in it that nearly concern the Court; and you know 'tis a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing to have Potent Enemies.</p>
            <p>Therefore I reſolv'd to ſend it into <hi>Holland,</hi> in hopes it would there be welcome: for every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy has an itching Ear for what paſſes in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly,
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:6"/>all Men gape after the Secrets of the <hi>Louvre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you meet with any Faults in reading this ſmall Hiſtory, be ſo kind as to remember, that 'twas a Lady that wrote it, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing partly ſuch Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as ſhe had ſeen with her own Eyes, and partly to deceive her ſolitary Half Hours. In the mean time, I ſhould be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to hear that ſhe had gain'd her Point; which
<pb n="*" facs="tcp:60948:7"/>was, to pleaſe your Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies with telling Truth, and which for that reaſon occaſion'd her Gadding abroad: aſſuring you, that merely that Satisfaction would make me gladly to forget the Trouble I have had to keep her ſecret in this Country.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60948:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SCARRON</hi> Appearing TO Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Poſture of the <hi>French</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs at this day, obliges the Moſt Chriſtian King, as every body knows, to keep fair with the Northern Crowns; from whom as he may reap great Advantages, ſo his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty neglects nothing to preſerve their Amity. Of which, his Officious Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity which he made appear in the magnificent Entertainments that he gave the Prince of <hi>Danemark,</hi> during his ſtay in <hi>Paris,</hi> was a ſufficient proof: and it may be ſaid, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> out-did it ſelf at that time; there
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60948:8"/>being nothing omitted to engage that Prince, and lock him to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> and all the reſt of the Court Ladies, had Orders from his Majeſty, to careſs him with all Imaginable Kindneſs; and therefore to charm the Prince's Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heart, ſhe reſolv'd to appear in a Ball, which the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for 'em in the Palace-Royal. This Ball had been preceded by a moſt Sumptuous Banquet, to which the Prince of <hi>Danemark,</hi> Monſeigneur the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> the Princes and Princeſſes were invited. Several Healths went briskly about; and the King's, and that of the Princes who were Kind to him in the Preſent War, in not entring into the Confederacy againſt him, were drank firſt: after which the <hi>Dauphin</hi>'s Health, and the Healths of all the Princes of the Blood went round, and then the Prince of <hi>Danemark</hi>'s, and that of the Young Princeſs of ***** his Miſtreſs. Preſently after this, the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance,</hi> whiſpering to the Prince, gave
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60948:8"/>him to underſtand the extream Joy of his Majeſty and the whole Court to ſee ſo perfect a Union, and ſo ſtrict an Amity between the two Crowns: to which he added, that the moſt prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing means to render that Amity and that Union eternal and and inviolable, was to ſee one day his Royal Highneſs wedded to a Princeſs of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Banquet being over, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for Dancing, and the Princeſſes appear'd with that Pomp and Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, that the like had never been ſeen. The Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> perceiving that the Company thicken'd by reaſon of a great number of Lords and Ladies that had not been invited, caus'd the Apartment, where he was together with the Princes and Princeſſes to be ſhut, and left the reſt of the Croud in the <hi>New Gallery</hi> of the Palace, with the Muſick, where they made up a ſecond Ball, and where ſeveral Ladies of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity were habited in Maſquerade. In the Prince's and Princeſs's Apartment, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Chartres</hi> being Queen of the Ball, took out the Prince of <hi>Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60948:9"/>ſeveral times to dance. Nor was any thing ſo charming as that Young Beauty, the Luſtre of whoſe Jewels drew upon her the Eyes of all the Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> whoſe Care did not a little contribute to the Good Order which was there obſerv'd, was taken out in her Turn by the Prince to dance, but ſhe refus'd him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay'd the Honour which he did her with a Profound Reverence, without ſtirring out of her Place. She anſwer'd the Prince of <hi>Danemark,</hi> who addreſs'd to her, That her Character of Governeſs of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> would not permit her ſo much Youthfulneſs; That ſhe was there only as a Spectatrix, for that ſhe had a long time ago, bid adieu to the Pleaſures of the World.</p>
            <p>Nor was her Anſwer to be wonder'd at, for in truth that Lady is at this day the Greateſt Pattern of Piety in <hi>France.</hi> However it were, never were the <hi>French</hi> Ladies ſo forwardly eager to make their Magnificence glitter in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60948:9"/>Eyes of Foreign Princes, as they were at that time. Toward Midnight ſeveral Pleaſing Metamorphoſes took place, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one appearing in diſguize and Maſquerade. The Prince of <hi>Danemark</hi> diſguiz'd himſelf like a <hi>Moreſco</hi> Slave, attended by Eight Lords that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany'd him in the ſame diſguize. The Prince's Patron, taking upon him to perſonate a <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> preſented him to all the Ladies of the Court, to ſee who would buy him, which occaſion'd the moſt pleaſing Paſtime in the World: and twelve young Engliſh Lords ſent by King <hi>James,</hi> appear'd at the ſame time like <hi>Quakers,</hi> which made all the Company Laugh, and was an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Addition to the Spectatours delight.</p>
            <p>After ſo many various Metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, at length appear'd a Lord diſguiz'd like a Devil. Nothing ever appear'd ſo hideouſly dreadful: the Diſmal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance was ſo terrible to the Ladies, but more eſpecially the Dutcheſs of <hi>Chartres,</hi> that they were forc'd to take a world of Pains before they could allay
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60948:10"/>the Commotions of her Fear; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her Condition, not ſo ſeaſonable for ſuch ſort of Spectacles, they were in terrible Fears that ſhe would have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry'd: but it ſo fell out, that ſhe was more afraid then hurt.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> by this time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving 'twas paſt one a Clock, retir'd firſt of all <hi>Incognito;</hi> and being got into her Chamber, ſhe call'd <hi>La Caverna,</hi> one of her Damſels, who ſpread her Toilet, and brought her all her Accoutrements to paſs away the Night. Now Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> is a Woman proper and delicately ſhap'd, plump, full Viſag'd, lovely Eyes, and about five and forty Years of Age, but ſtill appearing Young; Learned and extreamly Witty, well vers'd in the Lives of the Saints, but particularly in that of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> to which ſhe applies her ſelf with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Attention, reading in it every day an Hour or two before ſhe goes to Bed.</p>
            <p>By ſuch Pious Exerciſes as theſe ſhe has render'd her ſelf worthy the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60948:10"/>of the Holy Society: and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. from whom the Merit of this Lady could not be conceal'd, has vouchſaf'd her both his Heart and his Affections, which gives us a perfect De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the nice and delicate Judgment of that Prince: as having never ty'd himſelf but to Perſons of her Character. Conſider him in the Choice of his firſt Miſtreſs, Mademoiſelle <hi>de Machini,</hi> who was by no means hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and had the worſt Air in the World, but ſhe was infinitely witty; and they that had heard her but ſpeak, forgot all her other Defects. Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de la Valiere,</hi> had no leſs the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant over the Heart of this Monarch, even to the raiſing of Violent Paſſions in his Breaſt. But let us leave this Prince to his Tender Affections, and ſet what became of our Heroeſs Madam <hi>de Maintenon?</hi> After ſome moral Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ſhe took up a Book, entituled, <hi>Reflections upon the Mercy of God,</hi> by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Valiere.</hi> This devout Damſel having written the moſt curious Thoughts that ever were, and with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions enough to move the moſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60948:11"/>worldly minded; in thoſe Meditations it was that our Pious Marchioneſs was Exerciſing her Thoughts, when ſhe heard a noiſe in her Chamber. She thought at firſt it had been <hi>Diana</hi> her little Bitch; but looking behind her, ſhe ſaw a Man with a Night-Cap upon his Head, wrap't up in a Winding-Sheet. Who ſhould it be but her Husband <hi>Scarron,</hi> that Famous Author, whoſe touring Genius, and his Verſes, have made ſuch a noiſe upon the Earth, and who is ſtill no leſs good Company in the Kingdom of <hi>Pluto,</hi> accompany'd with three of his Friends, <hi>Rancune,</hi> carrying a <hi>Folio,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titl'd, <hi>[The Annals of Hell, wherein are contain'd all the most Secret Actions of Mortals.] La Rapiniere,</hi> who carry'd the Contract of Marriage before God and their Conſciences, paſs'd between <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarr,</hi> ſirnam'd <hi>God's Gift,</hi> and <hi>Frances d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigne,</hi> Widow of Mr. <hi>John Scarron:</hi> And <hi>Ragotin,</hi> who carry'd the Flambeau; but he, out of Reſpect, retir'd into the next Gallery. Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who was not a little diſmay'd to ſee ſo much Funeral Pomp, would fain have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60948:11"/>hid her ſelf in her Cloſet, had not the Ghoſt ſtopp'd her, crying out, Whither ſo faſt, Madam? Pray ſtay here a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and hearken to the grievous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the moſt Unfortunate of all Men. Since the Fatal Siſters cut the Thread of my Life, and my deſcent into the Lower Regions, I have done nothing but pin'd away, being all along tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Deſpair, and unconceivable Pangs of Grief, to hear every day, by all that thick and threefold arrive in our Territories from the Middle, Sides, and both Ends of <hi>Europe,</hi> the wicked Life you lead, and the Miſchief you have been the cauſe of, by your dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Counſels. 'Tis the Diſcourſe of all the Infernal Court; there is nothing talk'd of but your Name upon the River <hi>Styx,</hi> and you are the Mirth for the moſt ſerious Souls in their Six-penny Paſſages by that Black Water. You have ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly confounded my Reputation, to my irreparable Damage, in regard I am frequently in the Societies of the Poets, who are the rankeſt Scoffers in the World; and as often in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the Philoſophers, no leſs Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60948:12"/>and full of their Girds and Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms. One day, as I was muſing for ſome Thoughts proper for a certain Copy of Verſes which <hi>Proſerpine</hi> had commanded me to make, in Honour of Vertuous Women that had been always Conſtant to their Husbands, I flung out of that ſame dreary Academy, dull and moroſe, and not half ſo witty as I was wont to be in this World. Upon that, I walk'd a Turn or two in the Elyſian Field to refreſh my Brains, where <hi>Pluto</hi> met me, and ſwore to me, like a <hi>Beau</hi> of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd Deity, that as ſoon as ever he had yee in his Clutches, he would thruſt yee into <hi>Tartarus,</hi> the moſt dreadful Place in all his Dominions, and there excru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate yee with all the moſt exquiſite Torments that your Crimes have me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited. I was in a terrible Agony to hear him pronounce ſo diſmal a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Thereupon, I beſought him to grant me Audience, to the end I might obtain the liberty to give you a Viſit, on purpoſe to admoniſh yee to alter your extravagant courſe of Life, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent betimes, in order to your avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eternal Puniſhment. And now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60948:12"/>that Tenderneſs, all that is left, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the more Noble part, which I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had for yee, has made me take this long Journey, with three of my Friends: <hi>Anaximenes,</hi> one o our Philoſophers, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given us Air, as the Principal of all things, that we might appear Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real.</p>
            <p>Oh, Sir, (ery'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi>) how am I ſurpriz'd at the cruel Reproaches which you caſt upon me! Miſerable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that I am, what have I done, to be thus expos'd to the Anger of a Deity! Nothing can equal my Pains, nor the unfortunate Condition to which I am reduc'd: Heav'n and Earth conſpire againſt me, and my Name, it ſeems, is the Sport of Hell.</p>
            <p>What a pretty Art, Madam, you have to counterfeit and diſguiſe all your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triegues? but there is nothing conceal'd from us, in the Inferiour Regions. I will ſhew you in this Book, what you would be very unwilling to have known concerning your Amours, and all the other Particulars of your Life.</p>
            <p>Oh, — Sir, (reply'd Madam <hi>Maintenon,</hi>) you may perhaps be very much deceiv'd: 'Tis a long time ſince the Charms of this World have had any more then a feeble Operation over me; God having infus'd it into me, to betake my ſelf to a more ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Retirement, I mean, the beautiful Abbey of St. <hi>Cyr;</hi> to which I dedicate all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60948:13"/>the Days of my Life with a Pleaſure no way interrupted by the fading Allurements of the World, that enchant others without Intermiſſion. How ill grounded and unjuſt are all your Reproaches! I beſeech yee, tell me, what mean yee by thoſe Amours, and all thoſe Gallantries that ſupply your daily converſe with Merriment and Diſdain, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe gloomy Manſions where you now abide? I have heard you hitherto with a great deal of Patience; but I muſt tell yee, I look upon my ſelf as much abus'd; and could a <hi>Scandalum Magnaium</hi> reach yee, I ſhould make yee ſenſible of it; for I look upon my Conduct to be Exemplary, and that there is no fault to be found with me, as being the Model and Pattern by which ſo many young Ladies and Gentlewomen of Quality are to regulate and ſquare their Lives and Converſations.</p>
            <p>I am well inform'd, Madam, (reply'd <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>) who put it into the King's Head to erect that ſame <hi>What d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> and to do ſeveral other things prejudicial to his Honour, and the Repoſe of his Kingdom. The King hearkens to your Advice, and you are ſhe that guides the Chariot of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and his Government. Yet all the World too apparently ſees, that all his Conqueſts are hardly able to ſupport him. I remember I have obſerv'd in Hiſtory, that <hi>Hercules,</hi> who was once the moſt Illuſtrious and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ous of all the Heros of Antiquity, after
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60948:13"/>all his unparalell'd Atchievements and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits, at length became the Slave of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. His Love for <hi>Omphale,</hi> Queen of <hi>Lydia,</hi> was ſo violent, as to make him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change his Club for a Diſtaff, and ſpin in Petticoats among her Maids, only that he might have the opportunity to gaze upon her Beauty, and the Honour to be her Waiting-Woman. We read in the Hiſtories of <hi>France,</hi> that ſeveral of our Princes would have been happy, had they not ſuffer'd themſelves to be bewitch'd and poſſeſs'd by the Love of Women. 'Tis a Softneſs that effeminates the Courage of a Hero, and extinguiſhes the Luſtre of his ſublimeſt Qualities.</p>
            <p>Though you, Sir, in the Heighth of your T'other-World-Gravity, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) would fain make it out, That 'tis a Weakneſs for a Prince to love our Sex; yet we cannot forbear being ſo vain as to boaſt of it, when we make our ſelves the domineering Miſtreſſes of a Heart ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending in Value. There is nothing ſo charming as to Reign, and for a Woman to ſee her ſelf the Depoſitory of all the Secrets and Favours of a Court; to preſide, as it were, in Council, and to diſpoſe of the good or bad Fortune of the Courtiers. If all your Accuſations were true, you had ſome ground for what you ſay. But lay aſide theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe Thoughts; you wrong the Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Heart, and Great Soul of our Monarch; nor are you acquainted with his Humour,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60948:14"/>while you ſubject his Abſolute Will to Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Controul. 'Tis true, he vouchſafes me ſome Proofs of his Eſteem, in Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome Services that I have done him.—</p>
            <p>I ſee, Madam, (ſaid <hi>Scarron</hi>) by your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that you take it for a Celeſtial Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be belov'd by a King, and to find that all your Services are not repay'd with Ingratitude. But here it is that I muſt tax yee with a rank Oblivion of that Faith and Oath which you ſo ſolemnly ſwore to me, before God and Men, That you would never —never forget me after my Death; never— have any more Traffick with the World. But I find now, that you are no leſs inveigl'd and tranſported with the Vanity and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it, then a Girl of Eighteen: and that the dazling Glitter of a Crown has made yee forget your Extraction; as being beholding to <hi>America</hi> for Primitive Day-light, and the firſt Minutes of your Life. 'Twas enough for you to have been contented with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which I did yee, when I raisd yee from the Duſt of abject Meanneſs, and matchd yee to our Illuſtrious Family, the moſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of all the <hi>Scarrons</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) that the Obligations which you heap'd upon me were infinite; and I muſt as ſincerely proteſt to yee, That my firſt Knowledge of the King was extremely Innocent. You know that after your deceaſe, I kept my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60948:14"/>dark Chamber as diſconſolate as the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Matron. But I was low, and knew not which way i'th' World to turn me: ſo that after I had long mus'd upon my ſorrowful Deſtiny, I reſolv'd to look out for a Service; and one of my Friends promis'd to procure me a Place to wait upon a Lady, if I would go into <hi>Portugal:</hi> which Damſel liv'd at that time with Madam <hi>de Monteſpan;</hi> with whom I was often admitted to Chat, when I went to viſit my Friend, who did all ſhe could to bring me into the good liking of her Miſtreſs. One day that I diſcours'd with the Lady about Indifferent Matters, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd her to be well enough pleas'd with my Company; which infus'd into me ſo much Confidence, as modeſtly to beſeech her to recommend me to ſome Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. How! Mademoiſelle, cry'd ſhe, would you go to Service? — Moſt gladly, ſaid I, — for I can aſſure yee, without any Hyperbole, I was ſo caſt down for loſs of <hi>You,</hi> that I was for any thing in an honeſt way. At the ſame time, Madam <hi>de Monteſpan</hi> frequently receiv'd Letters from the King who then, and after that, moſt tenderly lov'd her. Being indiſpos'd one Evening, ſhe pray'd me to anſwer him. I obeyed her, but not without difficulty, as thinking my ſelf not fit to write to a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. This Modeſty of mine was quickly perceiv'd by the King, who is infinitely Witty; and next Morning he ask'd of his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60948:15"/>Miſtreſs why ſhe had not writ to him? She anſwer'd, That ſhe did according to Cuſtom, the Pleaſure of writing to him being too charming for her to neglect it. Ha! Madam (ſays His Majeſty, laughing) the Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of the Fair Sex is always acceptable to me; but tell me truly, who was it that did you that piece of Service? Madam <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſpan</hi> anſwer'd without Ceremony, that I compos'd the Letter, and ſhe copied it. From that moment, I tell you freely, His Majeſty hath always evidenc'd a great Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for me. Here is alſo the Copy of the firſt Letter which His Majeſty wrote to me.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The King's Letter to Madame <hi>de Maintenon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Did not believe, most Incomparable Lady that after I had ſeen all the Charming Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s of the Court, there had been any thing in the World that could have touch'd me ſo ſenſibly. The ſtrong Impreſſions which your rare Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities have made upon me, convince me, and accordingly I ſpeak it ſincerely, That a King would be advanc'd to the highest pitch of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, were he as much beloved by you as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> deſires. Do not then oppoſe your ſelf my Fairest to that which may render me happy; and be firmly perſwaded, that never any Man was ſo paſſionately in Love as I. The Pledges which I deſign to give you, my most An table Lady of a Love ſo ſincere and tender, are of a very
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60948:15"/>high Value, and merit your most tender Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The Crown and Scepter which I lay at your Feet, my Aderable Lady, are ſenſible Proofs of the high Paſſion which I entertain for you, <hi>Farewell, my deareſt Dear.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And to engage me further (continues Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi>) his Majeſty advanc'd me to the Quality of Lady-Governeſs to the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> his Brother the Count <hi>de Vexin,</hi> and the Mademoiſelles <hi>de Tours</hi> and <hi>Nantes.</hi> You cannot imagine what trouble I had to reſiſt all theſe obliging Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods which his Majeſty made uſe of, to bring me to be what I am.</p>
            <p>To ſay the truth, An Ambition to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf Glorious and Fam'd in the World, cancell'd all the Impreſſions which my Duty, or Marriage-Covenant, had laid upon me; but I love you ſtill, in ſpite of Death, which hath made a Separation betwixt us: And the greateſt part of my Converſation with the King, is, upon the Loſs I have ſuſtain'd of ſuch an Husband, who was the Glory of all the Wits of his Age.</p>
            <p>All thoſe Arguments which you bring, Madam, (replies <hi>Scarron</hi>) to make your Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence appear, don't juſtifie you in the leaſt; for you are ſtill a faithleſs Woman, and I am unhappy to hear you continually talk'd of: The Publick takes no notice of your private Treaty of Marriage, of which, look you, here is a True Copy.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60948:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Scarron</hi> calls upon <hi>Rapiuicre,</hi> and taking the Contract of Marriage, reads it before Madam <hi>de Maintenon.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="marriage_contract">
               <body>
                  <head>The Contract of the Private Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Lewis XIV.</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarr,</hi> ſirnam'd, <hi>The Gift of God,</hi> and <hi>Frances d'Aubigne,</hi> Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Council of Conſcience belonging to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſirnamed, <hi>The Gift of God,</hi> having moſt wiſely conſider'd that the ſaid Prince, together with the Dauphine, hath ſufficiently provided the Crown of <hi>France</hi> with Heirs, ſo that there's no reaſon to fear that it may fall to a Daughter, or that the Family of <hi>Bourbon</hi> ſhould be extinguiſh'd for want of Heirs Males. And moreover, there being no Princeſs in <hi>Europe</hi> upon whom his Majeſty caſts his Eyes, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a ſecond Marriage; and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty beſides thinking himſelf of ſuch an Age, as it is not convenient for him to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle any more with the Affairs of the World, becauſe of the particular Care which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to take for the Quiet of his Conſcience, and the Salvation of his Soul, by ſacrificing unto God, from his Heart, all the criminal Paſſions which have turmoil'd him from his Youth, till now.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60948:16"/>
                  <p>Theſe weighty Conſiderations prevail'd upon his Majeſty, with the Approbation of his Confeſſor, to caſt his Eyes upon <hi>Frances d'Aubigné,</hi> the Honeſteſt, moſt Vertuous, and moſt Pious Woman of the Age, that he might contract a Secret Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with her; by virtue whereof, thoſe Parties are inſeparably united together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and Holy Mother Church: And thereupon, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. promiſes henceforth to renounce all Commerce which he hath, had, or might have with other Miſtreſſes in time to come, and to acknowledge <hi>Frances de Anbigné,</hi> during the reſt of his Life, for his true and lawful Spouſe, to love her tenderly, and treat her with the ſame Reſpect as he did the late Queen <hi>Mary Thereſe,</hi> of happy Memory.</p>
                  <p>On the other ſide, <hi>Frances d'Aubigné</hi> promiſes before God; and Holy Mother Church, to be Faithful to his Majeſty, even to her Death; to Love and Obey him as a Faithful Spouſe ought to do her Husband.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty declares further, That on the Day of his Marriage he preſents <hi>Frances d'Aubigné,</hi> his future Spouſe, with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſate of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> that ſhe may carry the Title thereof during her Life; and doth alſo promiſe to found a Nunnery; under the Title of <hi>The Ladies of St. Cyr,</hi> whereof ſhe ſhall be Directreſs.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60948:17"/>
                  <p>The ſaid <hi>Frances d'Abvigné</hi> doth further engage, in conſideration of the Honour which the King hath conferr'd upon her, by advancing her to the Dignity of the Queens of <hi>France,</hi> to endeavour with all imaginable Zeal, by the Aſſiſtance of the Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> to extirpate the Hugonot-Hereſie, whereby ſhe may bring the Bleſſing of God upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's glorious Reign, ſo that all <hi>France</hi> may have cauſe to rejoyce in the happy Choice which his Majeſty hath made of ſuch a vertuous Spouſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>You ſee, Madam, (ſays <hi>Scarron</hi>) that your Honour is not preſerv'd by this Method: All the World look upon you for all this as a Harlot; and ſpeak of your Amours with the King, as they do of thoſe of his other Miſtreſſes. Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> formerly my Friend, hath perſuaded you, that by this ſecret Treaty of Marriage, your Converſe with the King would make leſs Noiſe; but his Deſign was, to deſtroy Madam <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſpan</hi>'s Intereſt, who was his Enemy, and by this means he ſurmounts thoſe Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which ſtand in the way of his Deſigns, and at the ſame time ſecures himſelf of the King's Favour.</p>
            <p>And beſides thoſe ſpecious Titles, of being Lady Abbeſs of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> and Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> both Eminent Qualities,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60948:17"/>make a great Noiſe in the World, and draw upon you inſenſibly all that People ſay of you.</p>
            <p>Ha! (cry'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> in anger) who could reveal to you this Secret? You told me, Sir, that you hear News every day from this World, by thoſe who arrive in yours: It could be none but the Marquis <hi>de Louvois:</hi> He acquainted you with this Contract of Marriage.</p>
            <p>Treacherous Villaian! This is but a ſorry Acknowledgment of his Maſter's Royal Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who ſpar'd nothing to raiſe his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to the heighth, firſt Miniſter and Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of State, Commander and Chancellor of the Royal Order: Are not theſe very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Titles? beſides a thouſand other Advantages which he receiv'd from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who honours him ſtill every day by a continual Regret for the Loſs of him. It is true, the King has great need of his Aſſiſtance in this preſent Juncture, to bear a part of the Fatigue which he endures by this preſent War.</p>
            <p>This War, Madam, (anſwer'd <hi>Scarron</hi>) which the King maintains with ſo much heat, appears very unjuſt before our Judgee of the Lower World, and againſt the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of all diſintereſted Perſons. That Prince having broke the Truce which he made with the Dutch for Twenty Years, baniſh'd all the Hugonots out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, revok'd the Edict of <hi>France,</hi> and acted a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60948:18"/>thouſand other things contrary to the Peace of a State.</p>
            <p>And not without good reaſon (continues <hi>Scarron</hi>) a part of thoſe Miſchiefs are charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon you, ſupported by Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> the ſworn Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Publick Peace; ſo that the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin has but too much reaſon to hate you, and call you his Step-Mother. You may remember many Affronts which you your ſelf put upon the Dauphineſs, and which did not a little contribute to the Diſtemper that carry'd her off: And King <hi>James</hi> II. of <hi>England</hi> is alſo indebted to you for the loſs of his Three Kingdoms by your pernicious Counſels.</p>
            <p>If the King has baniſh'd all the Hugonots from <hi>France</hi> (ſays Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) it was only to immortalize his Name and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, according to the Examples of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and <hi>Henry</hi> III. by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring, as they did, to extirpate Herefie, the King having a true Zeal for the Service of God.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and all the Cabinet-Counſel, poſſeſs'd him with the Apprehenſions of a general Ruine impending over his Kingdom, if he did not intirely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all thoſe Hereticks; and that he was never to expect the Bleſſing of God, if he did not bring back all thoſe poor Souls to our Holy Mother the Church. The King, whoſe Zeal for the Catholick Religion is Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, and which is altogether ſurpriſing in a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60948:18"/>Monarch who is at this day the Terrour of <hi>Europe,</hi> and juſtly pretends that all other Sovereigns ought to ſubmit to him, and hold of his Empire, ſubjects himſelf with a profound Obedience to all thoſe things with which Piety inſpires him. And by the Foundation of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> this religious Prince has given a Proof how much Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has the Aſcendant over him; for we may ſee that Holy Places, ſuch as Churches, ſubſiſt much longer in the Minds of the People, then Palaces, and Houſes for Civil Uſe.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, Madam, (anſwers <hi>Scarron</hi>) we ſee that for the moſt part, thoſe Princes who have ruin'd their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and People, are thoſe who have caus'd moſt Churches and Monaſteries to be built; witneſs <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> who fill'd <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Greece</hi> with 'em, after he had ruin'd and pillag'd all the Provinces of his Empire: And <hi>John Galeas,</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> who foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Charter-houſe of <hi>Pavia,</hi> the fineſt in Chriſtendom. Devotion is not always the true Mark of the Vertue and Bounty of Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and <hi>Henry</hi> III. his Brother, being cruel Kings, Men of ill Conduct, and no Juſtice, yet were the greateſt Bigots ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable in every thing by which they could merit Heaven; as, going Bare-foot on Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, in Pentients Habit, in the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> wearing coarſe Hoods, having Death's
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60948:19"/>Heads embroider'd upon their Cloaths, and ſhutting themſelves up in Oratories with Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits; yet all this external Devotion could not hide their bad Lives, and ill Government. It's always Glorious for a King to ſhew good Example to his Subjects; but <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is ſo far from doing ſo, that he imitates the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels in every thing.</p>
            <p>The ſtrict Alliance betwixt the <hi>French Court</hi> and the <hi>Ottoman Port,</hi> makes it appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that that Prince follows the vitious Manners of the Turks; inſomuch, that he copies their greateſt Crimes, and has made himſelf a perfect Muſſulman. We need go no further then St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> which may truly be call'd a Seraglio, under the Title of a Religious Nunnery; and I have no reaſon to doubt, Madam, that you are the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Inſtrument of a thouſand criminal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues which that Prince carries on there.</p>
            <p>And by this means you alſo procure to your ſelf a great number of Creatures throughout the Kingdom, among thoſe of Eminent Birth and Merit, who make their Court to you for an Alliance with thoſe Ladies, in hopes of obtaining conſiderable Employments by your Favour.</p>
            <p>Ah! Sir (cries Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) away with Thoughts ſo impious, and be not guilty of ſuch an Outrage againſt the Modeſty of that Holy Place. The King having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted me with the Conduct of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Militia, you wound me ſenſibly, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60948:19"/>ſin alſo againſt the Vertue of that Religious Prince.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Nobleſt and moſt Glorious Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that ever was heard of, to have ſo many young Damſels that want Eſtates, bred up at the Expence of that great Monarch; and though that agreeable Retirement be within a League of <hi>Verſailles,</hi> it may well be call'd a Holy Solitude, where nothing troubles their Repoſe. There is nothing there of that Magnificence which is to be found in the Palaces of Kings, but a noble Simplicity is its chief Ornament, and yet there appears in the ſame a thouſand beautiful Charms. When you ſee all thoſe young Ladies, and hear them ſing the Praiſes of Jeſus with ſo much Modeſty, you cannot but conceive an Idea of the bleſſed Angels, and holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in Heaven; and to ſpeak ſincerely, there's no Religious-Houſe where more of Order and Piety is to be ſeen.</p>
            <p>All things are ſo well diſpos'd in that Society, that Idleneſs is entirely baniſh'd thence: There they pray to God Day and Night; and thoſe Damſels ſeeing nothing but good Example, are bred incomparably better then they could have been in the moſt pious and regular Families. The King, who is the ſole Founder of that School of Chriſtianity, will always be the Admiration of his People; and by that Sacred Place, his Name and Memory ſhall be render'd Immortal.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60948:20"/>
            <p>In fine, Madam, (replies <hi>Scarron,</hi>) ſeeing the time when I muſt leave you draws near, and that <hi>Rancune</hi> and <hi>Rapiniere,</hi> my Friends, do ſignifie as much unto me, <hi>Pluto</hi> not having allow'd us any more time then what I have ſpent with you, we cannot go beyond his Orders; and I obſerve alſo that <hi>Ragotin</hi>'s Flambeaux is alſo burnt out. Make good Uſe of the Converſation which I have had with you; conſider that your Life paſſes away like a Dream, and that in a little time you may be ſummon'd before our ſevere Judges, <hi>Rhadamanthus</hi> and <hi>Minos,</hi> who will pronounce your Eternal Sentence.</p>
            <p>In what a terrible Condition will you find your ſelf, if you come to ſojourn in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Abyſs, for not having reflected ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly upon the Vain-Glory of the World, and the Counterfeit-Luſtre which attends its Honour. I perceive you are engag'd to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Courſe of the Great Ones; but if you have any remainder of Shame left, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to ſacrifice the Intereſt of the Court, and the King's Embraces, to your own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and mine: Retire into a Convent, as did <hi>La Valiere</hi> and ſpend the reſt of your days in the Service of God. The King being accuſtom'd to change, will treat you in the ſame manner as he hath done his other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>I aſſure you, Sir, (ſays <hi>de</hi> Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi>) that I have profited extremely by the good Advice which you have given me; and be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60948:20"/>perſwaded, that neither the Splendour of the Crown, nor the Glory of the Court, ſhall hinder me from acknowledging the Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs and Inconſtancy of this preſent Life; and I am very well ſatisfy'd, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be better ſaid, then what you have now ſpoken.</p>
            <p>You are ſtill the ſame for ſolid Reaſoning, and have loſt nothing of that ſublime and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therick Wit which procur'd you the Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all your Hearers. I wiſh that the Time allow'd you were longer, that I might enjoy your dear Preſence: But ſeeing it is weak to wiſh for Impoſſibilities, I had rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the precious Moments which remain; and I aſſure you, that I ſhall never loſe the Idea nor Remembrance of all your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p>The Moral which you have made uſe of to make me ſenſible of them, hath made a very great Impreſſion upon my Heart; but as to your Advice, of retiring into a Convent, 'tis impoſſible; for I am wedded to the King by indiſſoluble Bonds, and neither fear Change nor Diſgrace, having taken ſuch juſt Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that nothing but Death is capable to make a Separation; and moreover, I am more Sovereign then ever the late Queen was. But I can alſo tell you, That I never obſerv'd ſuch a Changeable inclination in that Prince as you imagin: He always lov'd thoſe very paſſionately, who had the good fortune to pleaſe him. I remember, that as to Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60948:21"/>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de Fontange,</hi> the King ſaid, one day, to the Duke of St. <hi>Agnan,</hi> That he was never ſo much in Love, and that according to all appearance, he ſhould never change.— But, Sir, (continues Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I would willingly have ſome News concerning that beautiful Damſel, and what Rank ſhe keeps in <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Kingdom of Darkneſs; for I can aſſure you, that his Majeſty was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mely griev'd at her Death.</p>
            <p>Madam, (ſays <hi>Scarron</hi>) I can tell you no other News of Mademoiſelle <hi>de Fontange,</hi> but that ſhe continually complains of you. The Prince, and the Marquiſs <hi>de Louvois</hi> look upon you as a wretched Woman, and ſay that you caus'd her to be poyſon'd, which has procur'd you a very bad Name in thoſe dark Regions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſerpine</hi> our Queen, was not griev'd when ſhe ſaw that beautiful Nymph arrive in her Kingdom; for ſhe is now the greateſt Ornament of her Court, and chief Maid of Honour.</p>
            <p>In truth Sir, (anſwers Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I want Words to expreſs my Aſtoniſhment, there muſt be ſome fatality in my Lot, for true or falſe I am always reckon'd guilty of whatever Miſchiefs happen at Court. But Heaven is the Witneſs of my Innocence.</p>
            <p>Madmemoiſelle <hi>de Fontange,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and the Marquis <hi>de Louvois,</hi> have had their Enemies ſince they believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have been poyſon'd; but being ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60948:21"/>Great Maſters of Reaſon as they were, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks they ought to have conſidered that Death ſpares none, of what Quality, Age or Sex ſoever. I think I have read that the <hi>Pagans</hi> erected Altars to all their Deities, and being ask'd once on a time, Why they had not erected one to Death, they anſwer'd <hi>Becauſe he was inexorable.</hi> I have ſtill one thing of Importance to ſay to you before we part, which I did not think on. You muſt know, Sir, that the Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits had no ſooner perceiv'd my being in Favour with the King, but they reſolv'd to gain me to their Party, they accoaſted me with all manner of Civility and Submiſſion, againſt which I was not able to ſtand out. They order'd the Reverend Fathers <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> and <hi>Bourdalon,</hi> to praiſe me to his Majeſty, and to inſinuate, that he could never have made a better Choice, nor one more worthy of his Converſation then he had done; by which thoſe Religious Fathers gain'd ſo much upon that Prince, that I found my ſelf oblig'd to receive their Viſits daily, and to teſtifie my Satisfaction therewith.</p>
            <p>I confeſs to you, that I had a Confidence in that Order, and therefore choſe one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them for the Director of my Conſcience, and could have been content to have born the Title of a Lady of the Society of Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and ſince that time Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been my Confeſſor in Ordinary, inſomuch that being at Confeſſion one day, I pray'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60948:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60948:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60948:23"/>him to pardon all thoſe Sins which I might commit with the King; and for this end I diſcover'd to him all the Secrets of my Heart. He was ſo far from blaming me, that he aſſur'd me I was not at all Culpable, and that it was no Crime to entertain an Amorous Correſpondence with the oldeſt Son of the Church, but that I muſt comply with that Monarch in ſuch things as he was moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly delighted with; that thoſe things which were call'd Sins with other Men, were not ſo in regard of Kings and Princes; that God had ſet them above the reſt of Mankind, that they might preſcribe Laws to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and that it was not lawful for any man to Controul them, but that their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects were bound to pay emblind Obedience.</p>
            <p>Juſt ſo, Madam, (ſays <hi>Scarron</hi>) Sinners do generally flatter themſelves, and find out Expedients to Extenuate their Guilt; but one may eternally Damn themſelves by ſuch a dangerous Practice, and thoſe are the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Leſſons which the Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits teach their Penitents of both Sexes; can one then make uſe of the Sacred Tribunal which ought to be an Aſylum for the Salvation of Souls to deſtroy them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly? I am not now ſurpriz'd at your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given up your ſelf with ſo much Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ſatisfie his Majeſty's Deſires, ſince you have ſo rare a Secret, and ſuch excellent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions from the Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> who tells you, that you may enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60948:23"/>an amorous Correſpondence without any ſcruple, and not be ſo much as guilty of the leaſt Venial Sin in ſo doing; that is the rare Morality which he learn'd from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>du Vaux</hi> his Tutor in Philoſophy, who hath ſince that, been advanc'd to the higheſt Preferments in the Order. 'Tis to him that he owes this fine Education and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his Fortune. I wonder much, how thoſe Doctors, who are apparently the Guides to Salvation and Lights of the Church, can reconcile this Conduct with the ſolemn Vows they are under to maintain Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>But the Reverend Fathers have a certain ſort of fine-ſpun Morality, which they don't teach publickly in the Schools; for in truth, as they ſay, It is not Convenient that all the World ſhould know it, and therefore they keep it in Reſerve for Great Wits, and ſuch as are capable of reliſhing the ſame. Theſe are the Myſteries which make them ſo much admir'd. Behold here what one of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Doctors ſays.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Scarron</hi> taking the Regiſter from <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cune</hi> ſhew'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> the Morals of the Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>When a man finds himſelf extreamly preſs'd with the Rebellion of the Fleſh, and and that an occaſion offers for an Amorous Rancounter, if he diſtruſt his own Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and be afraid that he ſhall not be able to prevent his falling into the ſame,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60948:24"/>that Perſon is guilty of no Crime, if he keep his whole Intreague ſecret to avoid worſe.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo another Remark of their Doctor <hi>Eſcobar,</hi> If you cannot prevent your Loving of Women, it is not ſo much as the leaſt Venial Sin to give your ſelf up to Love, for I know that it acts upon People with great Violence, and ſometimes puts them out of an Eſtate of Salvation. St. <hi>Francis Xavier,</hi> one of their moſt famous Religious Perſons, hath fully inform'd us of it during his Life, by all the Torments which he ſuffer'd; and therefore he ſays very Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly, That every man who ſins after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reaſon'd a little, his Faults are pardon'd, though with ſome more difficulty. Behold the Divinity of the Holy Fathers of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and the ſecret Doctrine which they teach their Diſciples!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scarron</hi> having ſignify'd to Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi> by bowing his Head, that he was not allow'd to ſay any more, being preſs'd by <hi>Rancune</hi> and <hi>Rapiniere</hi> to return to their ſhady Palace, left the Heroeſs in a profound Trance, reflecting continually upon the Converſation which ſhe had had with him, and the ſenſible Reproaches wherewith he had upbraided her.</p>
            <p>Ha! (ſays ſhe) if all the Ladies of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which I know, and who have loſt their Husbands, had ſuch Viſions as theſe, they would not take ſo much care to conceal their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60948:24"/>Intriegues; and if the King knew the Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation that I am in at preſent, I am ſure he would be touch'd with it, but he does not expect ſuch an Extraordinary piece of News.</p>
            <p>In this manner Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> paſs'd the Night without being able to ſleep; next Morning <hi>La Caverne</hi> her Maid entred her Chamber as uſual; and ask'd her Lady what ſhe would have her to do. The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs anſwerd in a diſcompos'd manner, That as ſoon as ſhe was dreſs'd, ſhe would go to St. <hi>Cyr.</hi> Some hours after ſhe took Coach to go to the Abbey, where St. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Ladies receiv'd her with incredible Joy, becauſe they had been depriv'd of her preſence for eight days time, that ſhe had been taken up with the King's Affairs, and particularly the Ball which the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> gave in the Royal Palace. Our Heroeſs having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd a little of what ſhe had to do, took a general Review of that ſine Houſe, and was ſaluted by all the Damſels with a Charming Modeſty, who accompany'd her four and four a-breaſt to the Church, to hear Maſs.</p>
            <p>The King, who is always impatient where he loves, bethinking himſelf that he had not ſeen his Miſtreſs in a long time, ſlew to give her a Viſit, without any Conſideration of St. <hi>Cyr.</hi> Into her Cloſet he went; and having ſaluted her after his uſual manner, that is to ſay very tenderly, he recounted to her all the Pleaſure he had taken at the Ball, imperfect only in this, that he could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60948:25"/>her Company till the end of it, and then ask'd her why ſhe went away ſo ſoon: tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her withal, That had ſhe ſtay'd but a little longer, ſhe might have ſeen the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt and moſt delightful Diſguizes in the World; for that the twelve Engliſh young Lords who were ſent by King <hi>James</hi> in the Dreſs of Quakers, eſcap'd a moſt terrible Danger; for that in making their way through all the Flambeaux that lighted that numerous Aſſembly, they miſs'd but very narrowly of being every one of 'em ſacrific'd to the Sport of the Night.</p>
            <p>You may have probably obſerv'd, Madam, (continu'd the King) in the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> what befell <hi>Charles</hi> VI. upon the like Occaſion, at the Nuptials of one of the Queen's Maids of Honour. At what time, ſome of the Noblemen dancing maſqueraded in the Shape of Bears, the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> holding down a Flambeau to look upon their Noſes, ſet fire to the Linnen that was joyn'd together with Pitch. Preſently the Room was all in Flame and Affright; the People crouded one upon another to get out, ſome cry'd, <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> but the Dutcheſs of <hi>Berry</hi> cover'd the King with the Skirt of her Gown, and preſerv'd him from the fiery Torrent. You ſee (ſaid the King, ſiniling) how uſeful Women are in this Life; for that by their Aſſiſtance we many times eſcape great Dangers.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60948:25"/>
            <p>Oh—Sir, (anſwer'd Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi>) if all Men had the ſame ſavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sentiments of us, we ſhould not be ſo much ſlighted as we are at this day. But we find that there are many Perſons no way inconſiderable for their merit, who ſtrongly oppoſe your Kind Opinon of us, while they aſſert, That Women are the cauſe of all the Miſchiefs and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes that happen in the World.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, (ſaid the King) thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have not been able to pay For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune a ſufficient Sallary, to procure 'em the Favours of the Female Sex. For my part I can aſſure ye, Madam, that were it not for Women, my Life would be but very burthenſome to me. 'Tis the ſweeteſt of all thoſe other Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that ſlatter our Sences. Which therefore ſeems to me, to be the reaſon, why Nature foreſeeing that we would make 'em the Objects of our Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, form'd 'em ſo amiable as they are.</p>
            <p>The King would have continu'd this Diſcourſe, but he was interrupted by one of his Gentlemen, who brought him Letters from the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgh</hi> and Maſhall <hi>de Bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lers.</hi> So that his Majeſty immediately took Coach
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60948:26"/>and return'd to <hi>Verſailles:</hi> where after he had ſpent ſome time in reading his Letters and returning Anſwers, He began again to reflect upon the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly Humour wherein he found his Miſtreſs. For in truth ſhe had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to him to be incredibly caſt down; ſo that the mighty Monarch not being able to penetrate the real Cauſes of ſuch an Extraordinary Penſiveneſs, wrote her the following Lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The King's Letter to Madam <hi>de Maintenon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DId I not Love ye, ſo well as I do, (Madam) I ſhould never buſie my ſelf to ſtudy with ſo much attention what could afflict ye to that degree of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure which I laſt beheld in your Countenance. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever pains I take to find it out. I cannot poſſibly divine the Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cauſe. You know how well I love ye, and that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I will ſpare to ſatisfie your
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60948:26"/>Revenge upon your Enemies. Adieu, Madam; ſpeedily let me know whatever it is that grieves ye, for I am Impatient till I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what it may be.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The King gave this Letter to one of his Pages, with Orders to carry it to Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who joyfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it, and return'd this Anſwer to it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Madam <hi>de Maintenon's</hi> Letter to the King.</head>
                  <p>OH! my dear Prince, in what an Extaſie am I, to find that you concern your ſelf ſo deeply in my Grief. 'Tis true, that I conceal the Real Motives of my Diſquiet: but there are ſome Secrets in this Life which we cannot unfold but with ſome kind of Torture; and this, of which you ſeek ſo earneſtly to be inform'd, is that of Nature. I can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing farther in This: but I ſhall reſerve all my Eloquence, till I happen to be alone in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60948:27"/>
            <p>Our Marchioneſs folded up her Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a more then Ordinary Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, and ſent it to the King, who read it two or three times, but all in vain; for he could not find what he ſought with ſo much earneſtneſs. The next Morning, his Majeſty went to St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> to viſit the King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> attended by ſeveral of the Nobility.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> who had intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of it, fail'd not to be there alſo in company with Mademoiſelle <hi>de Lui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and Mademoiſelle <hi>de Soubiſe,</hi> the moſt witty and moſt obliging Perſons in the World. But the King was not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſpoken with, and therefore while he was diſcourſing with King <hi>James</hi> and the Queen, <hi>M. de Maintenon</hi> went to walk with the Ladies. At what time, rambling from one thing to another, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>th they ſell by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; to talk of the little <hi>Cupids</hi> of Marble that flood in the  mid'ſt of the Garden And then it was, that Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de Luine,</hi> who is a Lady of a bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k humour, ask'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> why Poets and Painters had to ill repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented Love in the Figure of a Child;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60948:27"/>and what uſe he made of his Flambeau, and the Fillet about his Eyes; and that it would have been much more proper to have painted him a Young Man full grown, and in his flouriſhing Years.</p>
            <p>This Pleaſant Queſtion of Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de Luine</hi> put the Ladies into a fit of Laughter. You are as yet too young, Fair Lady, reply'd our Marchioneſs, to make a true Comment upon all the Figure that you ſee. Pardon me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if I undertake to unfold theſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and ſatisfie your Scruples. This Infant is a perfect Emblem of Love; that Paſſion in ſome reſpects being Weakneſs and Childhood it ſelf, and in others meer Dotage and Foppery: As for the Swathe about his Eyes, it denotes his Blindneſs, which is not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thoſe things that are moſt proper and convenient for him. The Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beau ſignifies that violent Heat which burns us in the moſt ſenſible Part of the Body, which is the Heart.</p>
            <p>Well, Madam, (cry'd Mademoiſelle <hi>de Luine</hi>) I ſhall take care, I warrant ye, to keep my Heart from being burn'd by any ſuch Flambeau's as that. Twill be very well, my dear Darling, (reply'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60948:28"/>our Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs) if you can. How far this diſcourſe might have led 'em no body c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n tell, for the Subject was allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring enough, but the King meeting 'em at the end of a wide Alley, put an end to it, and the Ladies taking another way, left the two Lovers by themſelves together. The King thus finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone with his Miſtreſs: Oh, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, (ſaid he) you have too unkindly prolong'd my Languiſhing Deſires to know the unhappy Occaſion of your ſo deeply Afflicting Sorrows. You know the tenderneſs that I have for ye; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you cannot, without a great deal of Injuſtice, conceal any thing from me.</p>
            <p>'Tis very true, Sir, (anſwer'd M. <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) your Majeſty's Kindneſs and Affection have been ſo ſingular toward me, that there is nothing which I can or ought to hide from your knowledge. Give me then leave to tell ye, that the other Night returning from the Ball, after I had been meditating a while in my Chamber, I heard a noiſe; but much more Terrible was my ſuddain Aſtoniſhment to behold the Gaſtly Appearance before my Eyes of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Scarron</hi> and three of his Friends.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60948:28"/>
            <p>How! Madam, (ſaid the King) do the Dead then begin to riſe before we come to the End of the World.</p>
            <p>I know not that, Sir, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) but I am ſure, to no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of mine, God knows, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to hold a Dialogue with him for above Two Hours.</p>
            <p>'Twas long enough in all Conſcience, (anſwer'd the King) for a Man without Fleſh and Bones; but all this while, what ſaid the Ghoſt to yee?</p>
            <p>Oh, Sir, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi>) the moſt grievous things, and the moſt abuſive and ſcandalous things that ever were heard. He Reproach'd me with an unparalell'd Confidence, that I had violated my Faith and Oath which I ſwore to him before God and Men; and that being belov'd by your Majeſty, I was lookt upon both on Earth, and in the Infernal Court, as a Woman without Reputation, or in plain Terms a Harlot; and that <hi>Pluto,</hi> the Prince of the Abyſs, has threaten'd already (the Holy Virgin keep me out of his Clutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) to make me feel the Effects of his Fury; and that <hi>France</hi> was beholding for all the Miſchiefs and Calamities that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60948:29"/>had befallen her of late, to the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pernicious Counſels which I gave your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>But that which moſt ſurpriz'd me was, that he ſhew'd me the Contract of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, by which you were ſo Good and Gracious as to eſpouſe me to your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; nor can I imagine how this Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom could come by ſuch a piece of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſie, and which your Majeſty took ſuch care to conceal. For my part, I muſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſitively accuſe the Marquis of <hi>Louvois,</hi> who moſt certainly has betray'd your Majeſty in the Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And for a further Accumulation of Grief upon Sorrow, he told me, That the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> Mademoiſelle <hi>de Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tange,</hi> and the Marquis of <hi>Louvois,</hi> aſſur'd him, that I had caus'd 'em to be poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd. Could any Man have ſaid any thing more Extravagant or more Injurious.</p>
            <p>Madam, (reply'd the King) I am ſomewhat at a loſs what Anſwer juſtly to return yee upon the Diſcoveries you have made me; nor can I readily believe theſe Things to be real: 'Tis only a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which perhaps you may have had in your Sleep, proceeding from ſome little Kindneſs which you may ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60948:29"/>for the Memory of that good Man.</p>
            <p>Sir, (anſwer'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) all that I have told yee is moſt certainly true: neither was I ever lookt upon to be a Viſionary.</p>
            <p>But, Madam, (reply'd the King) you made mention of the Marquis of <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vois;</hi> now you know that he has been a long time in the other World, and 'tis impoſſible the Dead ſhould know what is done in this.</p>
            <p>Oh— Sir, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I was always of the ſame Belief as well as you; but M. <hi>Scarron</hi> ſhew'd me a large Regiſter, which <hi>la Rancune</hi> brought along with him, wherein are contain'd all the moſt Secret Actions of Mortals.</p>
            <p>At the Word <hi>Rancune,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> the King fell a Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and ask'd her, whether ſhe knew what the Name ſignify'd.</p>
            <p>Sir, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) never believe the Names of <hi>Rancune, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piniere,</hi> and <hi>Rag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to be ſain'd like the Names of the Perſons in a Comedy. For they were M. <hi>Scarron</hi>'s very good Friends that always kept him Company in this World.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60948:30"/>
            <p>Why then it ſeems they take Journeys at pleaſure from the other World hither, (continu'd the King, with ſome kind of Aſtoniſhment.) And yet if I could ſee once more the Men and Women which I have loſt, it would be a Pleaſure to me beyond imagination. But I believe it not ſo eaſie a thing to riſe from the Dead; and yet methinks I could be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear ſome Tydings of poor Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>de Fontange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, (anſwer'd Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi>) 'tis a thing that I have ſtudy'd to bring to paſs as much as any thing in the World, well knowing thereby, that I ſhould oblige your Majeſty; for I am convinc'd of the paſſionate Love which you had for her; but I was troubl'd that ſhe had ſuch an ill Opinion of me.</p>
            <p>It may be, Madam, (ſaid the King) 'twas only a Scandal which that ſame <hi>Aeſep</hi> rais'd of himſelf. I always lookt upon Mademoiſelle <hi>de Fontange</hi> to be too prudent to harbour any ſuch groundleſs Thoughts; and for your part, Madam, I am ſure 'tis impoſſible but you muſt be innocent of ſo heinous a Crime.</p>
            <p>However, Sir, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) all this while I ſuffer in my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60948:30"/>Reputation, and in regard that M. <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> told me, how that beautiful Nymph is lookt upon with an Eye of Favour at the Infernal Court, and that ſhe is one of Queen <hi>Proſerpine</hi>'s Minions, ſhe may ſay what ſhe pleaſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Trifles, Madam, (ſaid the King) not worth your Thoughts. I rather am afraid leaſt <hi>Pluto</hi> ſhould fall in Love with her, and conſequently, leaſt the poor Lady ſhould incurr <hi>Proſerpine</hi>'s Diſpleaſure, the ready way to bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Head the dire Effects of <hi>Proſerpine</hi>'s revengeful Jealouſie.</p>
            <p>I do not believe, Sir, (reply'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) that thoſe ſooty Deities are capable of ſuch a noble Paſſion.</p>
            <p>How!— Madam, can a Perſon ſo witty, as you are, be ignorant how the Deities of old pin'd away and languiſh'd in the Fetters of beautiful Women! Their amorous Tranſports are known to all the World. Did not <hi>Jupiter,</hi> chief Sultan of all the Deities, transform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into a Thouſand Shapes, even of Beaſts themſelves, to bring about the Deſigns of his Concupiſcence: and all the other Demi-Deities, did they not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60948:31"/>imitate him with extraordinary Delight? If <hi>Venus</hi>'s little Baby had the confidence to diſcharge his Quiver into Heaven, What Reaſon is there to believe that Mortals are not ſenſible of his Wounds?</p>
            <p>I find Love, (continu'd the King) the moſt Noble of all the Paſſions: without it the World could never ſubſiſt. If I love an Admirable Object, I know I do no more then what my Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors did, being as little Inſenſible as they.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon it is, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) that I blame the King of <hi>Barathrum,</hi> and all his Subjects, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſaucy as to make your Amours their Hell-diſcourſe. I know, the time was once when <hi>Pluto</hi> was in Love him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and 'tis not unlikely but that ſome new Beauty may inflame his Heart at this very time.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, Madam, may very well be; but I know that the Prince of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> can never gain the Affection of Women. He was always ſo Deformed, and ſo ill a Courtier withal, that there was ne're a Hat-nos'd, Blubber-lip'd Nymph in the Roll of Antiquity, but ſcorn'd him. One Day therefore, in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60948:31"/>the heighth of his Deſpair, he bully'd away <hi>Proſerpina</hi> by force, as ſhe was pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Daſies in a Medow: and therefore I ſet my ſelf above a Thouſand petty Railleries that they can put upon me, let 'em criticize as much as they pleaſe. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Duke of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> who counterfeited a World of Godlineſs, deſir'd a Private Audience of me one Day; I conſented: but all the while he held me in a long Story of a Viſion of his, That the Kingdom would be turn'd Topſy turvy if I did not quit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>la Vallicre;</hi> adding withal, that he admoniſh'd me by a particular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God. And I, (ſaid I) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vize yee to take a particular Care of your Brains which are in a very ſad Condition, and to reſtore me all that your Uncle robb'd me of.</p>
            <p>The Duke made a low <hi>Congé,</hi> and ſneak'd away. By and by comes to me Father <hi>Anat,</hi> my Confeſſor, egg'd on by the Queen, to tell me, That he would leave the Court, for that my Trading in Love made too great a Noiſe. I ſmil'd, and bid him take his Liberty. But then the poor Father, finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf taken at his Word, would ſain have
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60948:32"/>turn'd Cat in Pan; but I told him, my Curate would ſerve my Turn for the preſent.</p>
            <p>You cannot believe, Madam, how all his Order teaz'd him for being ſuch a Ninny. I cannot endure ſuch a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Hypocrites, that take a Pride in reforming others, but ſpare for nothing to gratifie their own Pleaſures. For my part, I love Liberty in this Life.</p>
            <p>The King, who was in a good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, would have gone on, but he was oblig'd to return to <hi>Verſailles</hi> with the Lords and Gentlemen that attended him.</p>
            <p>After he was gone, Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi> went to join the Ladies again, who were diverting themſelves in a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race Walk, at a diſtance off.</p>
            <p>Ah, Madam, (ſaid Mademoiſelle <hi>de Soubiſe,</hi> what a while have you been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with the King.</p>
            <p>I aſſure yee, (reply'd our Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) I never i' my Life ſaw our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch in ſo good a Humour.</p>
            <p>All the Reaſon i' th' World, Madam, (reply'd Mademoiſelle <hi>de Luine</hi>) for you inſpire him always with Jocundry and Blitheneſs.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60948:32"/>
            <p>No, no, my Dear, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) 'tis not from my Influences that he derives his Gayety.— But here ſhe ſtopt.— Her Lacquey came to tell her, that the Coach atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the Gate, and ſhe had a mind to be at <hi>Verſailles</hi> that Night.</p>
            <p>But for all this, Madam <hi>de Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> could not be rid of her Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Her Husband had left her, but the Dialogue ſtill continually haunted her.</p>
            <p>The next Day ſhe went to wait upon the King at his Hour of riſing: And after they had diſcours'd together of ſeveral Things, ſhe told him with a ſad and lamentable Air, That ſhe could not Sleep for the Phantom that was always hovering before her Eyes; and that her Soul was in great Diſorder.</p>
            <p>The King, whoſe Heart is very Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Compaſſionate, in reſpect of his Miſtreſſes, bid her go to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Confeſſor, Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and impart her Afflictions to him.</p>
            <p>Immediately Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> call'd one of her Pages, and ſent him away Poſt to <hi>Paris,</hi> to tell the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prieſt, he was to attend the King. But he was not to be ſound; for he was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60948:33"/>gone to refreſh himſelf with his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Enjoyments, at his Houſe in the <hi>Fauxburgh</hi> St. <hi>Anthony.</hi> So that the Page return'd as wiſe as he went.</p>
            <p>Thereupon Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> without any more ado, made bold with the King's Cloſet; where, in a ſhort time, ſhe wrote the following Note, and ſent it away with all ſpeed: For her Conſcience was all this while upon the Rack.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon</hi>'s Letter to the Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AT length, Reverend Father, after long Muſing upon the unfortunate Accident that has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal'n me, I have caſt my Eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, as the Perſon from whom I expect my Deliverance; being fully perſwaded that you can rid me of the Torment which I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo. 'Tis not any Politick Affair nor any Intriegue that I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60948:33"/>am driving on, which engages me to ſend you theſe Lines. My Sufferings are inward, my Soul is harras'd with Remorſe of Conſcience. Haſten then to me with all poſſible ſpeed, dear Father; for you alone can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Peace and Tranquility of my Soul.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Page was no ſooner arriv'd, but one of Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi>'s Lacqueys car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd him into a Cabinet hung with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Work, where were alſo preſent the Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſeveral other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Father ſaw the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, he ſmil'd, believing he had ſome Meſſage to deliver to him from the King. To which the Page reply'd, That he was ſent from Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> to deliver him that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>'Tis all one; (ſaid the Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for Tydings either from the One or the Other, are equally grateful. And ſo reading the Note, with an Aire of Satisfaction, he told the Page, that he
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60948:34"/>would ſpeedily do himſelf the Honour of going to affure the King and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> of his moſt humble Reſpects and Readineſs to ſerve 'em. And indeed the Reverend Father took no ſmall delight to let all the Company ſee the Eſteem and Tenderneſs which he had for that vertuous Lady, by expaciating into a Panegyrick upon the gliſtering Vertues that adorn'd her Mind.</p>
            <p>And certainly it may be ſaid, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Aggravation, that among all the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> there never was a Perſon that underſtood ſo well to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with all the Humours, all the Fega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and all the Intriegues of the Court of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. with ſo much Wit, ſo much Policy, and ſo much Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. No wonder then that having ſo many Sleights and Ways to gain a Prince's Heart, we ſee him towring in ſo high a Sphere of Proſperity, and the Envy of his whole Order, who ſee him almoſt the ſole Poſſeſſor of the King's Ear, and by that means, with Eaſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting all Obſtacles that oppoſe his Deſigns.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60948:34"/>
            <p>Being then ſo eminent and ſo great a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſon, let us wait upon him to <hi>Verſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> where he arriv'd at what time the King was in company with Madam <hi>de Maintenon.</hi> The King no ſooner ſaw him, but reaching forth his Hand for him to Kiſs, Father, (ſaid he) you are ſhe moſt Happy among Men; you were wiſht for here with a more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Paſſion; every Hour was thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Day till you came.</p>
            <p>Sir, (reply'd the Reverend Father) with a Monkiſh Humility, all the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs that I have in this World, is to be belov'd by your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>The King was pleas'd with his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, and bid him take his Place. Their firſt Diſcourſe was about the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Affairs; but that being ſoon over, the Father turning toward our Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, In truth, Madam, (ſaid he) I have a long time had an extream deſire to enjoy the Happineſs of your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: Father <hi>Bourdalon</hi> has Preach'd two or three times, but you never wouchſaf'd him the Honour to hear him; which did not a little ſurprize me, knowing your Devotion to be ſo exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60948:35"/>
            <p>Truly Father, (reply'd Madam<hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I have been forc'd to kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my Chamber for ſome time, not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf very well: Beſides, I an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fallen into a deep Melancholy that very much diſturbs my Mind.</p>
            <p>May not the Cauſe, Madam, of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much Grief, (reply'd the Reveren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Father) be enquir'd into, and whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it derives it's Original?</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly, Father, (ſaid the March<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oneſs) I am firmly convinc'd, That the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is nothing that one of your true Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents ought to conceal from your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and that we ought to apply ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves to you, as to the real Comforte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our Souls. I'll tell yee then what '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that thus torments me. Monſieur <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> is return'd from the other World, and has laid thoſe Things to my Charge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that pierce my very Heart: For he told me, That he could not be admitted into Eternal Reſt, for that I had neglected him after his Death, not having caus'd Maſſes and Prayers to be ſaid for him ſufficient to releaſe him out of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miſery. And this is that which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts me extreamly, that I ſhould be the Cauſe of his Sufferings in Purgatory.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60948:35"/>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, Madam, (ſaid the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather) you tell me very ſorrowful News — But pray Madam, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong has he been Dead?</p>
            <p>As far as I can remember, Father, reply'd the King) he dy'd that very Year that I was marry'd to the deceaſed Queen, which was in 1660.</p>
            <p>Then, Sir, (anſwer'd the Reverend Father) we may reckon it to be about Thirty four Years that this poor Soul has been in fiery Tribulation. Good Soul!— ſufficiently Puriſy'd!— A Martyr in Purgatory.— We muſt intorm the Pope, that we may get him Canorin'd.</p>
            <p>His Holineſs, Father, might do well to put him in the Kalendar of Saints, and order his Bones, as a new Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, to be carry'd to all the Churches in <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> But pray tell me,— Is there a time limited for us to be in Purgatory?</p>
            <p>Sir, (anſwer'd the Father) we have no certain time appointed for our Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. We are confin'd to this Place, according to the demerits of our Crimes, For a longer or ſhorter time, ſufficient to purge us from all our Tranſgreſſions and Sins committed in this World: For
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60948:36"/>the Scripture tells us, That no Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can enter the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>But that which very much ſurprize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me, (ſaid our Heroeſs) is, that M. <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> ſhould be ſo long detain'd in this ſame Manſion of Pain; for I always found him to be a merry Soul indeed but full of Piety and Devotion: Beſides the good Man, being ſeiz'd with a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitick Diſtemper, liv'd many Year without the Uſe of his Limbs; by which means God gave him time enough to Repent.</p>
            <p>Repentance, Madam, (reply'd Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>la Chaiſe,</hi>) is the only means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Mercy of God. But in regard that as I told yee before, we muſt for all that, ſuffer out our Sufferings in the Place appointed for the perfect Expiation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Sins, I advize yee to uſe your utmoſt Efforts for this Martyr; to give Money ſpeedily to two or three Churches, to ſay a ſufficient Number of Maſſes for his Deliverance: 'Tis the ſureſt way to get his Soul admitted into Paradiſe. You muſt alſo your ſelf be continually at your Prayers to the Holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin and all the Saints, that they will
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60948:36"/>vouchſafe to put up their Petitions for him.</p>
            <p>What think yee, Father, (cry'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) if I ſhould undertake a Pilgrimage to our <hi>Lady of Deliverance,</hi> or perform ſome other Penance to get this wandring Soul out of Torment with all the ſpeed that may be. I would fain have him, I car'd not how ſoon, in the Saints Everlaſting Reſt, rather then be troubl'd with him here upon Earth</p>
            <p>Lord! Madam, (cry'd the Reverend Father) what Religious, what Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sentiments are theſe for a Woman of this World, and in your Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But I ſind that you have ſtill an unexhauſtible Spring of Piety in your Heart.</p>
            <p>Alas! Father, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon,</hi> with an extraordinary Aire of Modeſty, I am not ſo Devout as you take me to be.— The World, — the World, Father, will get the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in ſpite of all Reluctancy,— and I am continually waging War with the Rebellions of my Fleſh—</p>
            <p>Madam, (anſwer'd the Father, fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deep Sigh) we ſhall never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60948:37"/>till we get to Heaven, where we ſhall meet with no more Tryals and Temptations of this Life.</p>
            <p>I am apt to believe, Father, (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the King with a Smile,) that we have been at a Sermon: You have preach'd to us the beſt Morality i'the World. Nothing grieves me, but that I fear me it will have ſo ſtrong an ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> that ſhe'll forget all the Pleaſures of this Life, and we ſhall loſe her in theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Contemplations.</p>
            <p>I will tell yee, Sir, (anſwer'd the Marchioneſs) that there is an unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Joy to be met with, in the ſolid Contemplation of the Divine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For my part I no longer wonder that ſo many Souls of the Saints have been tranſported to Heaven in Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Enthuſiaſms. But this ſame Zeal. God knows, is not perfect in us; ſo that we may ſay, that we always feel in our Heart, ſomething that oppoſes right Reaſon</p>
            <p>Obſerve, Father. (ſaid the King) that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> never propoſes any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſhe alſo ſupports it with a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Proof, with ſo much Strength, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60948:37"/>Solid Reaſon, that <hi>Plato</hi> could have done no more. In all theſe Lovely Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, continu'd the King, beholding our Heroeſs with a wiſtful Eye, How pleaſant it is to hear a Perſon ſo witty as you are, argue ſo Pathetically. In good earneſt, I find the Fate of Men is very Frail, in reference to the Female Sex. But who can help it? The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Nature having given 'em a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Heart, and Senſes capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all Impreſſions, how is it poſſible for 'em to reſiſt ſo many Enemies? So that 'tis no wonder, if many times, in deſpite of our own Wills and Conſents, we ſuffer our ſelves to be ſurpriz'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis very true, Sir, ſaid the Reverend Father, that there it is where Human Weakneſs ſhows it ſelf, and in that we are more unfortunate then Criminal, ſince we are not able, as your Majeſty well obſerves, to Triumph over thoſe Senſes of ours, that without Intermiſſion oppoſe our Will. I ſind nothing in all St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Theology, that better agrees with the Frailty of Human Creatures, then when he ſays, that when he would do Good, evil is with him; but that he ſinds another Law that hinders him from doing what he would.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60948:38"/>
            <p>Father, reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> you have exactly hit the meaning of that Great Apoſtle, I am charm'd with this Diſcourſe, nor do I care how long it were to continue. But in regard his Majeſty has already Laugh'd at me, for taking ſo much pleaſure in theſe ſeeming Enthuſiaſms, I am afraid of provoking him, and rendring my ſelf in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure troubleſome.</p>
            <p>No, no—Madam, reply'd the King ſmiling, I am too great a Lover of what you delight in, to oppoſe your Holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations. Beſides, that a Converſe wherein you intermix ſo much of your own Wit, and ſo engaging, can never be otherwiſe then moſt agreeable to me.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid our Marchioneſs, I am infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely beholding to your Majeſty for that Eſteem with which you Honour me; and I return thanks to Heaven for my Good Fortune, and for that ineſtimable Minute, wherein I had the Felicity to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your Favour. But your Majeſty always exerciſes a ſort of Goodneſs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to your Royal Inclination, which is to excuſe all the Defects of the moſt humble your Servants.</p>
            <p>The King was about to have return'd
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60948:38"/>an Anſwer, but a Page brought Word, that the Cloth was laid. So that, now they minded nothing but Eating and pleaſant Diſcourſe. The King began the Reverend Confeſſor's Health; and he carried it to Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who receiv'd it very obligingly. Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being over, Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> who has the Honour to accompany the King every day at Dinner, took his Leave of the King, alledging the neceſſity of his Return to <hi>Paris</hi> to his Profeſs'd Houſe, where he gives Audience twice or thrice a Week to ſeveral perſons of all Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that come to kiſs his Hands.</p>
            <p>Said the King to him, I give you leave to go home, but upon Condition that you return in the Evening. Upon which the Father Tranſported with the King's Civility, diſplay'd his Acknowledgment by a profound Reverence, and a Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity attended with an extraordinary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
            <p>After he was gone, the King went to <hi>Fontainbleau,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and the <hi>Dauphin</hi> to make a Hunting Match in the Forreſt of <hi>Vincennes.</hi> In the mean time, our Heroeſs retir'd to her Chamber, to muſe at Leiſure upon
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60948:39"/>her intended Pilgrimage to our Lady of Deliverance. But before her departure, ſhe ſtay'd three Weeks in her Abbey, from whence ſhe went every morning in the Habit of a Penitent to the Great Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> to Order the ſaying of Maſſes for the Ghoſt of <hi>Scarron,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only by <hi>La Caverne,</hi> who waited on her in her Chamber.</p>
            <p>But the Marchioneſs was not content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Legion of <hi>Oriſons,</hi> which ſhe caus'd to be power'd forth in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral; for ſhe ſet all the Devout People at Work in ſeveral other Churches; more particularly at St. <hi>Euſtachius</hi>'s, and the Abbey of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> for whom ſhe had a ſecret Veneration. After all theſe Mortiſiations, ſhe went the next day to St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> to prepare the Ladies of the Abbey, and all the young Damſels to live in her abſence, with great Reſerv'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and with all the Diſcretion imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, giving 'em to that purpoſe the moſt admirable Precepts in the World. They took their Leaves of her, full of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Affliction for their Cruel Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from her dear Preſence. And at length, when thoſe doleful Complements and Formalities were over, ſhe took
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60948:39"/>Coach with <hi>La Caverne,</hi> in Order to her Travels, which were to be for a Month. 'Tis not to be imagin'd, what Floods of Tears her Abſence coſt the whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; but then the ſorrowful Siſters ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac'd themſelves again, with the hopes of their beloved Abbeſſes Return in a ſhort time: Aſſuring themſelves, that her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and her Devotion would ſecure her from all Attempts upon her Perſon, either of her incens'd Husband, or <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>The King, who ſtay'd at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> with an incredible Impatience to ſee his Miſtreſs before ſhe departed, could not readily reſolve to want her Company for ſo long a time; and diſputed warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with himſelf, whither or no he ſhould grant her Requeſt. But as he was mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and pondering upon this mournful Journey, for by that Name he call'd it; the rather, becauſe his Majeſty was no Admirer of Penances and Pilgrimages, Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> made her Entry, to pay him her laſt Adieu's, with a Sorrow ſurpaſſing all Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>The King Embracing her, Ah, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſaid he, how dear will this Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of yours coſt me! Thoſe Words
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60948:40"/>went to the Marchioneſſes heart, and overcame her with ſuch a piercing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolation, that for a time ſhe could not ſpeak.</p>
            <p>The King, who had his Reaſons for what he did, had let fall this on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For he knew that ſhe ſtood in need of his Aſſiſtance upon ſeveral occaſions.</p>
            <p>Before they parted for good and all, Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> ſettl'd all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Suſpitions, by a thouſand char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Proteſtations. The Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> who by good luck Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd juſt in the nick of time, beſtow'd au infinite Number of Benedictions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, to encourage her in her Noble deſign: Aſſuring her, that he would not ceaſe to offer up his Prayers to God, and all the Male and Female Saints, that they would be pleas'd to depute a good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel to be her Companion and Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and that he hop'd the Succeſs of her Pilgrimage would be greatly to her Glory. Adding withal, that it was a good Office of a high Nature, which ſhe was going to do for her Husband. Thus it was, that <hi>Pyramus</hi> and <hi>Thisbe</hi> ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with mutual aſſurances, never to be forgetful of each other.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60948:40"/>
            <p>The Father, who was an Ear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all theſe Proteſtations, ſtay'd behind with the King, diſcourſing for ſome time about the Marriage of <hi>Boufflers</hi> with Mademoiſelle <hi>de Gramont,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Antony Charles,</hi> Duke of the ſame Name, and whoſe Dowry was no leſs then 40000 Livres, beſides a Magnificent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the King in Jewels; and ſome talk of ſeveral other conſiderable Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luments.</p>
            <p>But let us return to our Monarch, who was extreamly turmoyl'd and unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be ſo long a Widower, as one that was never Idle in his Amours. Therefore, to paſs time away, he went every day to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> to Viſit the Queen of <hi>England.</hi> He found that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs well Built and very Charming, and that ſhe had a Heart not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of his Careſſes. And indeed, her deplorable Condition, after her Husband had loſt his Crown, cans'd her to entertain the Careſſes of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, with a more then ordinary ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, as being the moſt probable fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſupport of a King's unjoyntur'd Widow; ſo that his Majeſty ſucceeded perfectly to his Content. For one day
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60948:41"/>that King <hi>Jame</hi> was at <hi>Paris,</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had the Opportunity to be all alone a whole afternoon with the Queen, and to make her a Formal and Ample De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of his Love.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great's Declaration of his Love, to the Baniſh'd Queen of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WERE it for that Reaſon, that I muſt be accounted one of your moſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Enemies, I could not forbear to Careſs the misfortune, that brought you ſo happily into this Kingdom, and which has, by that means, procur'd me the Charming pleaſure of your Company. I muſt needs declare to you, Madam, that ever ſince that Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate day, I have always preſerv'd a moſt profound Eſteem for your Perſon, which has bred up and cheriſh'd in my heart, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that I can hardly tell what it is. I fancy to my ſelf the moſt pleaſing Idea that ever was in the World, of all your Spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Qualities, and I take delight to recall 'em to my mind every Minute of the day, and to Dream of you in the Night. I have habituated my ſelf to that which appears to me the only thing that aſſwages the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances of my Love; that is to ſay, an
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60948:41"/>unfeigned Vow which is made to your ſelf, by the moſt paſſionate of Men, and who burns with an Ardent deſire to let you ſee, how far it is poſſible for that Paſſion, which he has for you, to extend it ſelf.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Queen was not a little at a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus, to hear ſuch inforcing and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Expreſſions; which was the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſhe could not return a ſuddain Anſwer; for it behov'd her to look well about her on every ſide. She was afraid leaſt her Husband ſhould take notice of the King's Tenderneſs, and leaſt Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> ſhould turn her mortal Enemy, to whom ſhe had been infinitely beholding, during her abode in <hi>France;</hi> foreſeeing alſo, that her Succor might be very neceſſary ſtill; and for that in her Afflicted Condition, it became her to make uſe of all her Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Precaution to preſerve her friends.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, it was not in her Power to look upon the King with an indifferent Eye; She felt within her ſelf an Inclination ſtrong enough to love him; beſides, the Offers of his Service, and the continual Aſſurances of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Word, never to forſake her, and to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60948:42"/>uſe his utmoſt endeavours for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of her Husband; all theſe Conſiderations ſtagger'd the Reſolutions of her Chaſtity, and turmoyl'd her with a thouſand various thoughts.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the King, to whom the Queen had not as yet open'd her Lips, ſince the Vow that he had made her, firſt breaking ſilence, Madam, ſaid he, I know not to what cauſe to attribute the diſturbance which I behold in your Looks, or whither I may be able to make a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conſtruction of it.</p>
            <p>To which the Queen, not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Courtly Addreſſes of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, and no leſs willing to keep him in hopes, that one day he might ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Gainer of the Conqueſt to which he aſpir'd; Sir, ſaid ſhe, after a moſt Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and engaging manner, The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions you have made uſe of, to let me underſtand the Condition of your Heart, have plung'd me into a deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation; and I can hardly believe, that a Prince, like you, who are the Terror of all <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhould be in want of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Objects, to Sigh for a Perſon, whom Fortune has ſo ſeverely handl'd. My Misfortunes are daily before my Eyes,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60948:42"/>and the Fatal remembrance of 'em will never leave me till Death.</p>
            <p>Madam, reply'd the King, it would be in vain for me to reiterate what I have ſo often repeated over and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; that I am deeply ſenſible of your Misfortunes, and that they never yet could make me looſe the leaſt reſpect which is due to your Birth. I look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you ſtill as a Queen and what is more, abſolute over the Empire of my Will; and the ſecret Charms which I have diſcover'd in your Perfections, the force of which is inevitable, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd me to acknowledge the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which I ſuffer. Among a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Beauties that appear at Court, I do not meet with thoſe ſubduing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, which I find in you, and by which I perceive my ſelf ſo mortally Wounded.</p>
            <p>The Queen was about to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd an Anſwer, and to have let his Majeſty know, how infinitely ſhe was beholding to him, for his kind Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Favours beſtow'd upon her, when King <hi>James,</hi> who had been at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> to Viſit Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> came in and ſpoyl'd a good Complement. The
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60948:43"/>Reverend Father, it ſeems, had carry'd him to his Houſe in the <hi>Fauxburg</hi> St. <hi>Antony,</hi> where they had ſpent the whole day together, and where among other things, they fell into Diſcourſe about the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo by degrees, into a deep debate, which was the moſt probable way for the King to regain the three Kingdoms he had loſt. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father, whoſe Brains are Fertile in Counſel and Intrigues, had diſplay'd upon that Subject, the whole extent of his Eloquence, promiſing the diſtreſſed King all the Aſſiſtance, that he was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to afford him. Thoſe Aſſurances ſo ſincere and profitable, had warm'd the Unfortunate King's Heart, and brought into his Countenance an Air of Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, which accompanied all his Actions. In this humour, entring the Room, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaid he, you've a Bleſſed time on't, to be always courting the Ladies. 'Tis very true, reply'd his Majeſty, they have a powerful Aſcendant over me.</p>
            <p>The Scene of the Diſcourſe being thus Chang'd, King <hi>James</hi> fell into a long Story of the Fathers kind Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the various Subjects upon which they had been conferring Notes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60948:43"/>and the wholeſome Conſolations he had receiv'd from that ſame Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-Director. He extoll'd his Wit and his Merit, and applauded his Majeſties Choice of ſuch an Excellent Father Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</p>
            <p>But our Monarch, who had other Things to trouble his Brains withal, then the Encomiums of Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> look'd upon K. <hi>James</hi>'s Chat as imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; as being altogether uneaſie in his Mind, and not knowing how his Affairs ſtood in the Heart of his New Miſtriſs, who was no leſs diſpleas'd with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption on her Side: And in this humour the King took his leave with only a Farewel, Brother, till I ſee you again. King <hi>James</hi> waited upon him to his Coach, where he pay'd him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Complements, and pray'd him to continue his wonted Goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him; and the King aſſur'd him he ſhould be always the ſame.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> he abandon'd himſelf wholly to his Amorous Paſſion, revolving in his mind all his Miſtreſſes Charms, and the Obliging Ways by which ſhe had engag'd his Heart, were the Subject of his Ruminations all that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60948:44"/>Night. The next Morning he return'd with an Unconceivable Impatience to reviſit the Object of his Love. But foreſeeing, that perhaps he might not have a favourable Opportunity to find the Queen alone, ſhe being Viſited by the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and Madam <hi>de Noailles,</hi> her Intimate Friends, he wrote her the following Lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Kings Letter to the Baniſh'd Queen.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce I was born, I never lov'd ſo much as now I do; my Love for you is of another Nature then what I was wont to feel upon the like Occaſions. This Violent Paſſion can proceed from no other cauſe then from your Merit, which diſtinguiſhes you from other Women. Never ſay then, Madam. that this is the uſual Diſcourſe that Men make uſe of, to inveagle the Fair and Beautiful, ſince the Troubles of my Heart, and the reſtleſs Diſquiet of my Mind continually prove the contrary. Anſwer my Love more
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60948:44"/>kindly then hitherto you have done; aſſuring you, that if you afford me the leaſt Hope, I ſhall quickly find Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Adieu Madam.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Queen receiv'd this Letter with an extraordinary Joy; but ſhe did not think it proper to return an Anſwer: which very much diſturb'd the King; and made him reſolve to return that day to St. <hi>Germains.</hi> He found the Queen in her Cloſet, reading an Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Hiſtory ſent her out of <hi>England;</hi> to whom, Madam, ſaid he, I draw ye from a more pleaſing Divertiſment. To which the Queen made anſwer, that not having elſe to do ſhe took a Book in her Hand; but that now ſhe would make a better uſe of the happy Hour that preſented it ſelf, to enjoy his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Company.</p>
            <p>The King whoſe Paſſion was Violent, ask'd her in a kind of Diſorder that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently befalls true Lovers, why ſhe had not written to him; and told her withal, that ſhe had reduc'd him almoſt to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſpair to find his Love ſo ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay'd by a Perſon ſo Amiable; and that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60948:45"/>he had great reaſon to bewail his Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not having ever Sigh'd in vain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The Queen, who is Witty, and ready at Replys, told him that her Husband never parted from her all that Day; and that his Majeſty having a Love for Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> ſhe was unwilling to draw upon her ſelf the Hatred of a Rival, who might trouble that little repoſe that was left her.</p>
            <p>The King, who is an utter Enemy to Arguments and Reaſons where he Loves, told her that he had power ſufficient to preſerve her from all her Fears; that he had a high Eſteem for that Lady; but that he ſtill preſerv'd a Tenderneſs for an Object of Adoration: and that the Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon</hi> had too much Diſcretion to contradict him in his Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer of that Nature ſplit the Queen's Heart, and inſpir'd her with ſeveral thoughts, that might have carry'd her a great Way; but the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi>'s Arrival deliver'd her out of her Perplexity; and the King, who is very Complaiſant in Ladies Society, tack'd the Converſation together for a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60948:45"/>long time, ſo that the Day paſs'd mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily away. They fell into Diſcourſe of the French and Engliſh Cuſtoms, and of other things very diverting. But the Evening drawing on, as jealous of their Happineſs, brake off theſe pleaſing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, and ſeparated the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Company.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who was by this time got ſafe to our Lady of Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, upon <hi>All Saints</hi> Eve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and tyr'd with her Journey, having travel'd half the way a foot in the Habit of a Penitent, went to a Houſe of one that was her Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, with her Damſel <hi>La Caverne,</hi> who was no leſs weary then her Miſtriſs. The Lady of the Houſe was very much ſurpriz'd to ſee that ſuch a Perſon, as ſhe was, ſhould undertake ſuch painful Mortifications; but the Marchioneſs up and told her the Important occaſion of her Pilgrimage: That her Husband <hi>Scarron</hi> had appear'd to her, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided her; and that ſhe was to ſay ſo many Maſſes for him: For this Reaſon, ſaid ſhe, my Dear Friend, I am come hither to Pray to the Patroneſs of your Pariſh, the <hi>Mother of Deliverance,</hi> to aid me in my preſent Affliction. To which
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60948:46"/>the Lady anſwered, that ſhe was the beſt Saint in the World, and that ſhe wrought ſeveral Miracles every Day, and that of all thoſe that beſought her with an Ardent Zeal, ſhe never ſent any one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, without ſome effect of her Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>The next Day our Heroeſs lay all Day long i'th Church, (which was a great Teſtimony of her Piety and Zeal) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually and moſt Ardently imploring the favour of the Saint in the following form of Prayer.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
               <body>
                  <head>The Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon</hi>'s Prayer to our <hi>Lady of Deliverance.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>een of Heaven, Guide to Salvation, Refuge of Afficted Souls, take Pity of Me, and of Him, whom I recommend to thy favour, and who has lain languiſhing for theſe thirty Years in Purgatory; and who perhaps without thy Succour muſt be for'd to ſtay there till <hi>Doomſday:</hi> Send me not back, dear Mother of Mercy, without Affording me ſome Sign of thy Protection. I recommend the Soul of Monſieur <hi>Scarron</hi> into thy Hands, and beſeech thee to admit him into Paradiſe. This is the only favour, which a Miſerable Penitent, Devoted only
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60948:46"/>to thy Service, begs at thy Hands. Pardon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne my paſt Tranſgreſſions, and all thoſe Sins, which I ſhall commit for the future: Safely direct all the Deſigns of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Good King; and ſo order it, that he may obtain Victory over his Fnemies, and particularly over the <hi>Huguenots</hi> that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane thy Holy Name. Thou knoweſt how much I love the Light of the Eaithful; and that I put all my Confidence in thy Divine Power: Now then ſhew it, by giving Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to this Martyr, who muſt otherwiſe be a perpetual Slave to his Torments.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>She alſo ſaid a world of <hi>Ave Maria</hi>'s, which brought up the Rear of all her Pious Ejaculations. In theſe Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Devotions the Day was ſpent; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, ſhe was preſent with a moſt Religious awe, at all the Prayers that were ſaid to the Ghoſt of <hi>Scarron.</hi> The Feſtival being over, our Marchioneſs, who is as Generous as the Sun, ſcorn'd to depart the Holy Place, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Civil Preſent to our Lady of <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance,</hi> from whom ſhe expected ſo much eaſe. She therefore preſented her with an Infinite number of Wax Tapers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the Prieſt, who was to ſay the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60948:47"/>to let 'em burn Night and Day, as many as he thought ſitting for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Saint; which ſhe left to his Diſcretion, well-knowing that he would not cheat her for all the World. Madam, anſwer'd the Prieſt, you may return with full Aſſurance, and believe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> think my ſelf extreamly happy, that 'tis in my power to be Serviceable to a Lady of your Quality; beſides, that 'tis a matter of Conſcience. This humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply mollify'd the Heart of Madam <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maintenon,</hi> and drew out of her Pocket a little Purſe full of Single Money, which ſhe preſented to the Prieſt, conjuring him by all that was Sacred in the World to pray to God and all the Saints continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for her poor Deceaſed Husband.</p>
            <p>The next Morning, our Heroeſs ſet forward again in order to her return for <hi>Paris,</hi> very well ſatisfy'd and almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the Good Succeſs of her Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. Upon her arrival at <hi>Paris,</hi> the King was over joy'd to ſee her; He told her, that the Time of her Abſence had been very tedious to him; that ſhe had perform'd ſuch an Extra ordinary Penance, that ſhe could not queſtion the Succeſs of it, and that he believ'd that <hi>Scarron</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60948:47"/>was by that time in Heaven; or elſe he was certainly the moſt Miſerable of all Mankind.</p>
            <p>To which, Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deep Sigh, reply'd, that having done her Doty, ſhe leſt the Reſt to the moſt Bleſſed Virgin to whom ſhe had recommended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Martyr a thouſand times: So that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all that Dy'd were to give the Living ſo much Trouble, there would be no felicity in this Would.</p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledge, Madam, reply'd the Monarch, that Purgatory is a thing which very much perplexes me; for when we have done all we can do in this World, we know not, when we are about to die, whither we ſhall go.</p>
            <p>Sir, anſwer'd the Marchioneſs, your Majeſty cannot chuſe but know that Good Works and Penances are of great force to moderate the Pains of Purgatory, and to avert the Anger of Heaven that hangs over our Heads; and in regard I know that M. <hi>Scarron</hi> had never any Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for theſe ſort of Mortifications; his Genius carrying him rather to Jollity and Mirth, I am firmly perſwaded that this is the Reaſon why he is kept ſo long in Purgatory.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60948:48"/>
            <p>'Slife, then cry'd the King, what an Unhappy Man am I, Madam, who love the Pleaſures of this Life, as I do, and whatever is capable to Charm the Senſes; and find but a very feeble Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in my ſelf, God knows, to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Mortifications; what can I expect but to burn Eternally in the Fires of Purgatory?</p>
            <p>Sir, reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> your Majeſty carries things a little too far. I find ye extreamly Godly, and full of Devout Sentiments for Religion. You have perform'd a moſt noble Action of late Days, in Extirpating the Hereticks out of your Kingdom, and cauſing the Catholick Church to Triumph. Theſe Great Exploits will never dye; but will Infallibly carry ye to Heaven without any danger of Purgatory.</p>
            <p>This is that indeed which comforts me a little, Madam, ſaid the King; for God knows, the real Motives of my Deſign were grounded upon the Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Faith.</p>
            <p>While the King was yet ſpeaking, in came King <hi>James,</hi> his Spouſe, and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> being newly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>Verſailles</hi> to Congratulate our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60948:48"/>Heroeſs upon her Return from her Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, which ſhe had conceal'd from them, as being unwilling that any Body ſhould know it. Ah, Madam, ſaid the Queen, ſaluting her, you keep your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fars very Private. I ask'd the King ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Times, what was become of ye; but he would needs perſuade me all along, that you were ſtill at St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> which I could hardly believe, becauſe I never met ye abroad.</p>
            <p>You know, Madam, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Devotion are or ought to be carry'd Privately; and that our Works of Piety are then moſt Meritorious, when they make leaſt Noiſe.</p>
            <p>You muſt not take it ill then of the Marchineſs, reply'd the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> that ſhe kept her Pilgrimage Private, for Reaſons of Conſcience: we muſt do all we can to purchaſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, anſwer'd K <hi>James,</hi> is admirably well ſaid: but you muſt agree with me, that there are ſome Perſons born under bad Conſtellations; and that frequently thoſe Stars ſhed down their Malignant Influences upon us in ſuch a manner, that 'tis Impoſſible to avoid 'em.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60948:49"/>My Misfortune is an Apparent Proof of what I have ſet forth. For all that I did in <hi>England,</hi> while in poſſeſſion of the Crown, was only out of a Deſign to labour the Propagation of the Faith, to Reform the Laws, Poliſh the People, and to have done many other Things of that Nature; Nevertheleſs you all ſee what I got by it.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid the Dutcheſs, what you have told us, would carry us too far; it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves too long Reflexions; and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject being Mournful would beget a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation that would Kill us with Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly. Our buſineſs is to divert Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who looks as if ſhe came out of the Monuments. Let us all go to Morrow, if his Majeſty pleaſes, to chuſe King and Queen at <hi>Marli,</hi> and put a New Crown upon the Head of our Unfortunate Prince.</p>
            <p>All the Company applauded the Dutcheſſes Motion, who is Miſtriſs of the moſt Engaging Charms in the World, and who has the knack to win Affections when ſhe pleaſes her ſelf: And here it may be proper to let the World know, who this Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> was, that Enſlav'd the Heart of <hi>Charles</hi> II.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60948:49"/>till Death. She is Daughter to the Marquis <hi>de Keroues,</hi> a Perſon of Quality in <hi>Britany,</hi> who had loſt much of his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, before he got his Daughter into the Service of the Princeſs <hi>Henrietta Stuart,</hi> where the K. of <hi>England</hi> ſaw her the firſt time, and Lov'd her ever after.</p>
            <p>But to return to that Part which was acted next Day at <hi>Marli,</hi> where there were a great Number of Lords and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to Solemnize that ſame Courtly-Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival, the K. who was in a good humour, ſpoke a thouſand pleaſant things to the Queen; Nor could he retain from giving her Signes of his Paſſion. Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> ſeem'd a little Nettled at it; but being very Politick, ſhe diſſembled it. Abundance of Healths were Drank, and K. <hi>James</hi> was K. of the Ceremony. Whereupon our Prince ſaid, ſiniling, that he was mightily pleas'd that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had ſavour'd him ſo well, and that he was diſingag'd from his Word: For that he had often promiſed to make him King, and reſtore him to his Throne; and now he had no Reaſon to complain: adding, that to convince him further of the care which he took for his Welſare, he would entertain him with the Merit
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60948:50"/>of the Dutcheſs of <hi>G—on.</hi> K. <hi>James</hi> anſwer'd with an Air of Gayety, that he did not deny but that he had been touch'd with Love and reſpect for that Amiable perſonage. I know it very well, Brother, repli'd our Monarch, that you had an Extraordinary reſpect for her, and I agree with you that we are created to Love the fair Sex. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> diſplay'd her ſparkling Wit upon many occaſions; and particularly in ſuſtaining the Kings Sentiments, who ſate near to the Queen, and the moſt Paſſionate of all Mankind; but the Princeſs being afraid of her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal, ſeem'd to be tormented with Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie upon this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>The K. who is Sagacious enough, perceiv'd it at firſt, and to convince her that he was above thoſe Little things, he pull'd out of his Pocket ſome Verſes which he had made for her in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, telling her very pleaſantly that he was happy in a Lovely Muſe, which made him oftentimes have a mind to play the Poet, and that ſometimes he took a Ramble with her to <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi> Look ye, ſays he, what ſhe has inſpir'd me with to Day, But he preſented them to the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60948:50"/>Queen in ſuch a very Earneſt and haſty manner, as diſcover'd the Confuſion he was in. The Princeſs receiv'd them very Civilly, and read theſe words,</p>
            <q>
               <l>My Tender Heart fair <hi>Iris</hi> hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd,</l>
               <l>He who hath ſeen her, can't for Love be blam'd:</l>
               <l>How amiable are thoſe Charming Eyes!</l>
               <l>And yet how Guilty, Monarchs to Surprize.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This laſt Blow was Like to have caus'd Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi> to die for Grief, but her Love not being ſo Nice as to endure no Sharer, ſhe comforted her ſelf the more eaſily, being unwilling to oppoſe the pleaſures of her Prince, as preferring her Fortune and his Good Will to all the pleaſures of an Amorous Amuſement.</p>
            <p>The Day being ſpent in ſuch agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diverſions, every one took leave of each other. The K. attended the Q. of <hi>England</hi> to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> and our Marchioneſs was fully reſolv'd to return back to her Abby. As ſoon as ſhe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, all the Ladies of St. <hi>Louis,</hi> and the Young Damſels embrac'd her tenderly,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60948:51"/>ſignifying that her abſence was inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable to them. Our Heroeſs, on the other hand, aſſur'd them, that ſhe had had her ſhare of the Grief, and ſuffer'd no leſs then they, having continually thought on her Spiritual Militia; and as it was not long ſince ſhe return'd from her Pilgrimage, ſhe had always a ſtrong Inclination to ſee them again; but could not prevent her ſtaying ſometime at the Palace of <hi>Verſailles</hi> to pay her reſpects firſt to the King, and that now ſhe was to be more at St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> being oblig'd to pray further to God and St. <hi>Louis</hi> for Monſieur <hi>Scarron,</hi> that he might have a ſpeedy entrance into his deſir'd reſt.</p>
            <p>Although the King, and all the Ladies whom I have mention'd, did their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to remove the Marchioneſſes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, nevertheleſs ſhe abandon'd her ſelf to a Continn'd Penſiveneſs. Two mighty things did conſtantly ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in her Mind, the Reproaches where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Scarron</hi> had upbraided her extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Admonition which he gave her, as to the Changeable humour of that Prince, and the inconſtancy of his Love to any particular Object, as finding always Variety of new Charms,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60948:51"/>which preſaged that ſhe ſhould have the ſame fate with others of his Miſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Laſt Words of <hi>Scarron</hi> had made a mighty Impreſſion upon the Mind of our Heroeſs, and the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which befell her on the day of the three Kings at <hi>Marli,</hi> did fully confirm her in her thoughts, eſpecially when ſhe reflected upon the pleaſure and tranſport, which his Majeſty diſcovered in preſence of the Queen of <hi>England;</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd her, that her own good Fortune was not to be of any long duration, if ſhe did not behave her ſelf with great Complaiſance and Conduct. She very often blam'd the Inconſtancy and Volatile humour of Men, whoſe Love is guided by their Senſe, and laſts no longer then while the beloved Object is able to Charm them; it being Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to lay any Solid Foundation upon their Conduct. She conſider'd alſo, that the Weakneſs of a Woman was Great to yield up what is moſt Dear and Valuable to her in the World upon ſuch falſe Appearances; confeſſing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly, that a true Friendſhip had a thouſand times more ſweet Attractives and laſted till Death; that Love was
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60948:52"/>only a Paſſion begot by the preſence of an Amiable Perſon, but that Friendſhip was a Virtue which Sympathy fix'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two Friends by their Mutual care of, and continual Services to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thoſe Moral Reflections oblig'd our Marchioneſs to ſpend ſeveral days in great Solitude, although ſhe aſſiſted at the Maſles which where ſaid for <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>'s Soul, with all her Damſels at Saint <hi>Cyr,</hi> every Day according to Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> and Father <hi>Bourdalon,</hi> who had not ſeen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Maintenon</hi> after her return, being taken up with Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, were impatient till they had given her a Viſit; whereupon they took Coach and went to her Abby, where our Heroeſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them very Agreeably after her Devout and Modeſt manner. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers made known the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which they had to hear of her Arrival, and that apparently her Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney had been happy, for they had not ceas'd during her Abſence, to Pray and make Vows for her and Monſieur <hi>Scarron,</hi> whoſe Soul muſt needs be now in the Enjoyment of the height of Bliſs.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60948:52"/>
            <p>I wiſh it be ſo, Fathers, anſwer'd our Marchioneſs, with all my Soul, for that's the true reſt to which all of us ought to Aſpire, there being nothing in this Vaſt Univerſe certain nor Solid; we often poſſeſs Grandeur without tranquility, and pleaſures without repoſe, our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not being able to ſurmount all thoſe Obſtacles which oppoſe themſelves to thoſe good things, ſills us with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Cares, which give us perpetual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, Madam, replys Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> we have that ſhare of Reaſon which ought to diſtinguiſh us from other Animals, and direct us here to find Remedies for thoſe things which torment us.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Father, ſays our Heroeſs, but Reaſon, of which we make ſuch a Noiſe, affords but a ſmall aſſiſtance againſt our Paſſions and the Troubles of Life; It oppoſes it ſelf to all, but overcomes nothing; Tears our Hearts with a thouſand Remorſes and perpetual diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, and thoſe are all the effects which it produces by its ſevere ſtrength.</p>
            <p>If it be as you ſay, Madam, anſwer'd the Reverend Father, the Beaſts are
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60948:53"/>happier in their Innocence then we; for they follow their Natural Inclination with great Tranquility, and never feel any thing of thoſe troubles which Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition or Intereſt create within us Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Men.</p>
            <p>You have ſpoke Excellently well, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſays Madam <hi>Maintenon,</hi> for we have reaſon to Envy the quiet and ſweet repoſe of thoſe peaceful Creatures; and conſider that all the Advantages, which we brag of with ſo much Vanity, are not equal to their Living without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward trouble.</p>
            <p>But, Madam, Anſwers Father <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalou,</hi> that Tranquility is all the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which theſe Animals enjoy in their being, for their Soul dies with their Body, and returns to its firſt nothing.</p>
            <p>In truth, Father, if it were not the hopes which we have that our Souls are Immortal, and that after this Life we ſhould enjoy a peaceable Repoſe, we ſhould be more to be pitied then the Brute Beaſts; but I believe that thoſe Sweets and Joys ſhall be only diſpens'd, according to our Good Works, which I do always believe to be Meritorious.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:60948:53"/>
            <p>It is certain, Madam, Anſwers the Father, that our Works juſtiſie us before God, and that they Merit not only Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, but likewiſe an Augmentation of Glory; and we can alſo ſatisfie the Puniſhment due to our Sins by our own Sufferings.</p>
            <p>Then Father, ſays Madam <hi>Maintenon,</hi> 'tis of great Importance to a Believer to Labour with Great care for Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by a continual Penance, and to do many Good Works to augment their degree of Glory.</p>
            <p>Madam, replys Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> God hath Elected us, as having foreſeen our Works, and the Good Motions of our Free Will; for the Converſion of a Man is in part due to his own Natural Strength, and not wholly to Grace.</p>
            <p>But, Father, Anſwers our Heroeſs, If there be any Perſons perſectly Juſt in this World, ought they not to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of their Salvation.</p>
            <p>I will tell you, Madam, Anſwer'd the Father, that Believers may fall from the Grace of God, and periſh finally. But we hope ſtill that by our Mortifications, our Penances, and the Pains which we endure in Purgatory, we may co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60948:54"/>Paradiſe, for our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath deliver'd us from the Guilt, but not from all the Puniſhments due to our Sins. We muſt then be purg'd by the Expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Faults and endure thoſe Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and this is what the Children of God are to expect when this Life is ended.</p>
            <p>I aſſure you, Father, anſwer'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>Maintenon,</hi> with a Penitent Viſage and Tone, that ſuch thoughts as thoſe do entirely cool my Heart, take it off from all the pleaſures of this Life, and make me Groan earneſtly for a Holy Solitude, where I may Work out my Salvation without any Interruption.</p>
            <p>Madam, ſays the Reverend Father, what we ſaid was not a deſign to affect you, as it plainly appears to have done. This is only Diſcourſe; We ought not to underſtand the Articles of our Faith in ſuch a rigid manner, we muſt take up a milder ſort of Morality; and moreover, a Perſon ſo Young and Charming as you are, is not oblig'd to abandon the Pleaſures of Life ſo ſoon,</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60948:54"/>
            <p>In the mean time, Father, ſays the Marchioneſs, I begin to diſreliſh them, and if it were not for the Engagements I am under to his Majeſty, I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire my ſelf out of the World for the reſt of my Days, and go into a Covent; and I muſt Confeſs, that I have a mighty Inclination to the Capuchins: I envy the happineſs of thoſe Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they Live in much Devotion and Auſterity, and every Day before they go to Bed they ſay a Roſary, with the Litanies of the Holy Virgin, all which Piety Charms me Extreamly.</p>
            <p>But, Madam, Anſwer'd Father <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalou,</hi> methinks you have reaſon to be contented, ſeeing you enjoy an Abbey, wherein you may carry your Devotion to what height you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>True, Father, repli'd our Heroeſs; but in this Society I am divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt my Devotion and the World, and ſometimes cannot be private, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the continual Care which I muſt have of the Youth, and the Orders I muſt give out every Day to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity. I tell you freely, that that does oftentimes vex my mind.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60948:55"/>
            <p>Juſt as the Father was going to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, a Gentleman from the King Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> and was Conducted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Marchioneſſes Cloſet, by one of the Penitent Siſters, which broke off that Converſation, and oblig'd the good Fathers to return to <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Marchioneſs ask'd the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man what his Majeſties Commands were; who anſwer'd, that he pray'd her to come to <hi>Verſails</hi> to morrow.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who knows above all things how to take her Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, went to wait upon His Majeſty next day, who was the moſt Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly and out of Humour that could be, upon Monſieur <hi>Catinats</hi> Arrival at <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſails,</hi> to regulate the State of the War for next Campagne, after his Marriage with Mademoiſelle <hi>de Dangeau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After Dinner, Our Monarch to divert himſelf, went with Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi> to the D. of <hi>Orleans;</hi> where were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Danphin, the D. of <hi>Chartres,</hi> the Ducheſs of <hi>Nouailles</hi> and Ducheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> with many other Ladies and Lords; and being the time of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nival, they play'd all day. After Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, thoſe in Masks came in to Dance,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60948:55"/>but retir'd betimes, referring it to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Seaſon, becauſe there had been a Comedy, in which were Repreſented all the Celeſtial and Rural Deities, with their Royal Equipage and Extraordinary Machines upon the Theatre.</p>
            <p>The firſt Scene was a Plain, encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd with an Infinite Number of Trees juſt Budding, which ſurniſh'd a moſt delicious Shade in that Solitary Place. Theſe are the Names of the Gods which appear'd there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Time</hi> with a Hunger Starv'd <hi>Countenance,</hi> devouring every thing he met with; the very Stones not excepted: <hi>Jupiter</hi> darting Thunderbolts, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Univerſe in Obedience; The Sun environ'd with a thouſand Lights, and his Oracles, was mounted on a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot drawn by the Hours; <hi>Mercury</hi> the God of Eloquence, Ambaſſador and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter to all the Gods with Wings at his hands and feet, and a Caduceus in his hand, twiſted with two Serpents, to denote Peace and Concord; <hi>Bacchus</hi> on a Triumphal Chariot drawn by Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres cover'd with Deer-Skins, his Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Adorn'd with Leaves of Ivie and Vines; <hi>Mars</hi> the God of War and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60948:56"/>Arm'd Cap-a-pee, having a Helmet on his Head, a Lance in one Hand, a Pike in the other; <hi>Neptune</hi> with his Trident, ſitting in a Great Scallop-ſhell for his Chariot, and being drawn by Whales and Sea Calves; the Tritons half Men and half Dolphins, attended him Sounding a Trumpet made of the Scales of Fiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pluto</hi> with an Infernal and Gloomy Air, marcht before the Old Ferryman <hi>Charon,</hi> who receiv'd into his Barge without diſtinction, all thoſe that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd in the other World, and had by his ſide a horrible Dog, with Three Heads crawling full of Serpents. The Furies follow'd after, with Burning Flambeaux, ſoming with Rage, their Eyes ſparkling, and inſtead of Hair, had their Heads cover'd with dangling Vipers.</p>
            <p>Sleep bringing quiet Repoſe to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, attended by one of the Officers, called <hi>Morpheus</hi> the God of Dreams, who drew all ſorts of Figures.</p>
            <p>The Theatre chang'd Scenes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented a pleaſant Meadow, enamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thouſands of Flowers; and there all the Goddeſſes appear'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cibele</hi> Queen of the Earth ſate
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60948:56"/>Crown'd with Cities, and a multitude of of Trees and Animals. Round her was <hi>Juno</hi> in the middle of Kingdoms and Riches, follow'd by <hi>Hebe</hi> the Goddeſs of Youth, who continually fill'd out Nectar for <hi>Jupiter</hi> to drink.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pallas</hi> Arm'd all over, having a Lance in her hand, with the Liberal Arts, and the Sciences for her Ornaments; ſhe was follow'd by <hi>Diana</hi> Goddeſs of the Woods, and Huntſmen carrying a Bow and Arrows, with her Nymphs attending her. <hi>Venus</hi> the Goddeſs of Love and Senſuality, an incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Beauty, was drawn in a Chariot with Swans and Doves, and followed by the three Graces her Daughters. After her came <hi>Aurora</hi> Laughing, in a Guilded Chariot, with her roſie Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to proclaim the Coming of the Sun; ſhe was followed by Blind For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, having Honour and Riches in her Power, and managing a Wheel which ſhe turn'd about without ceaſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flora</hi> was in the midſt of a fine Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, which produc'd a thouſand Flowers, careſs'd by the <hi>Zephyri,</hi> which never abandon her; and <hi>Proſerpina</hi> with her other Nymphs, who are always buſie in gathering Poſies.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60948:57"/>
            <p>The Third Scene repreſented Mount <hi>Helicon, Parnaſſus</hi> the Fountains of <hi>Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocrania</hi> and <hi>Aganippides</hi> Conſecrated to the Muſes, <hi>Apollo</hi> ſate in the middle of that pleaſant Solitude, compoſing Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Airs and Verſes.</p>
            <p>Upon the Mountain ſate <hi>Pan,</hi> God of the Shepherds, with his Beard. Goats Feet, and Horns on his head, playing on a Melodious Flute. The Goat-footed Fauns and Satyrs, danc'd ſeveral Giggs with the Neighbouring Nymphs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> the God of Love, hover'd pleaſantly over this Illuſtrious Aſſembly, fluttering his Wings with extraordinary Delight and Sweetneſs, but maliciouſly ſurveying all the Arrows in his Quiver, with a deſign to Wound all the Heroes and Heroeſles. He thought fit to Wound <hi>Jupiter</hi> as the moſt ſenſible, and metamorphos'd him into all ſorts of ſhapes, as aſſuming the form o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Ball, carrying <hi>Europe</hi> on his back and paſſing the Sea; at another time into a Showre of Gold, deſcending through a Power of Braſs to the fair <hi>Danae;</hi> then into an Eagle to Raviſh young <hi>Ganimedes,</hi> and putting himſelf into all Shapes conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60948:57"/>for his Gallantries; ſo that we muſt ſay here with <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that we muſt not be ſurpriz'd at thoſe Natural Inclinations, to which Love carry men, ſince the Deities themſelves give us Examples of it.</p>
            <p>All thoſe Gods and Goddeſſes were the Idols of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> who moreover believ'd, that the Air was full of Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Gods or Demons, and imagin'd that they did ordinarily imploy themſelves in humane Affairs. They paid them homage every day, becauſe of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Vertues and extraordinary Merits, coming very near, ſay they, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the other Deities; and they did ordinarily Conſecrate a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon to them, as a Mark of their Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to which they were Arriv'd, as may be ſeen in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> where <hi>Cleome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> was eſteem'd a God by the Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, becauſe they ſaw a Serpent come out of his body after he was put to Death. All thoſe Fictions did ſtrongly ſeize the Spirits of thoſe people, and the young following the Example of the Old, made one of the Ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſay, that Man was a True Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal of Imitation.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:60948:58"/>
            <p>But we muſt leave thoſe thoughts, and return to our Theatrical Piece, which was made deſignedly, and by the Dauphin Commanded to be repreſented by the Kings Comedians, on purpoſe to divert thoſe diſquieting thoughts, into which that Monarch falls many times in a day, upon the Account of <hi>France,</hi> which lies deſolate on all ſides, and cries out, that it can do no more, if Heav'n don't Bleſs it with a favourable Aſpect.</p>
            <p>Another conſiderable diſquitet, which he Labours under, is how to find Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to maintain ſuch a preſſing War; but all thoſe Reflexions don't hinder the King and Court from diverting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if they were in the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Peace. Every day a thouſand pleaſant deſigns are formed to pleaſe the Ladies. The Comedy enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd them a long time in Charming Sports of Wit. All the Princes and Lords taking a mighty pleaſure to give proofs of their fine Genius, by drawing Morals from the Figures repreſented, and applying them conformably to their Inclinations.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:60948:58"/>
            <p>I don't find ſince <hi>France</hi> was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by Kings, that there has been any Reign more like this of <hi>Louis</hi> XIV. then that of <hi>Hen.</hi> III. When Pleaſures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, in ſpite of the Miſeries of the Kingdom. Senſuality Triumph'd, and led all other paſſions Captive. When that Prince had tri'd all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements which Nature had form'd, and deni'd himſelf nothing which could Charm his Senſes; he went in Pennance with all his Minions and Lords, to the Convent of <hi>Auguſtins,</hi> and to the Great Church of our Lady, two and two, like the Votaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Avignon,</hi> clad in White Holland, in the ſame manner that is obſerv'd by the Religious Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities.</p>
            <p>In this Proceſſion, the King marcht without Guard, or being diſtinguiſh'd from others, either by Habit or Order, the ſingers went before, cloath'd in the ſame Livery, and Singing the Litanies of the Bleſſed Virgin Melodiouſly. All thoſe Pious Penitents being Arriv'd at Church, Sung <hi>Salve Regina</hi> on their Knees in Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Muſick. The Great Rain which laſted the whole day, did not hinder
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60948:59"/>them to perform thoſe Myſteries and Exemplary Ceremonies, tho' their Hoods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were Wet through to the Skin.</p>
            <p>'Tis ordinarily the Genius of the moſt Voluptuous, to give ſome ſhare of their time to Devotion, to make it appear by that External preciſeneſs, that their heart is always fill'd with good Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and that all the Pleaſures which they are taken up with, bear no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Piety.</p>
            <p>I cannot leave this Subject, without taking notice how well <hi>Henry</hi> III. could make his Devotions and Senſuality a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, by an unuſual Sympathy. After having us'd divers Mortifications, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Feſtival of <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> where he was Solemnly preſent. The Week following, he made a Feaſt for the Duke his Brother and the Lords and Captains who accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him at the Siege of <hi>Charite,</hi> who were ſerved by all the fineſt Ladies of the Court clad in Green and in Mans Habit, and all the Gueſts were Cloathed in the ſame, being follow'd by Pages and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60948:59"/>Gentlemen, Cloath'd in like manner; ſo that, there was bought in <hi>Paris</hi> and other Towns, 60000 Livres worth of Green Silk for the Solemnity.</p>
            <p>It may be ſaid without Hyperbole, that this is to carry on their Criminal Pleaſures too far, and a very ſorry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment to Heav'n for its Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Men in General have Natural Weakneſſes, with which they can in no manner be Reproach'd, without refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon the firſt Cauſe as Unjuſt, God having ſiniſh'd and bounded his Nature: It is not in the Power of Man to ſurmount his Infirmities; but we muſt diſtinguiſh well, betwixt Natural Defects, and thoſe acquir'd by Habit or Imitation. The Latter may be cur'd by care, and our endeavours by good E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, to form a ſecond Life in our ſelves; for to continue always in Evil, is not to Live.</p>
            <p>I have leſt my pleaſant Company to employ their Wits. Let's now ſee, what our <hi>Heroeſs</hi> is doing. We ſhall find her Labouring under Jealouſie, not that ſhe Loves the King ſo intirely,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60948:60"/>but that ſhe is afraid, leſt her Rival ſhould carry off ſome part of her Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and ſhare in her good Fortune. After ſhe had well ruminated on the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant humour of the Prince, and reaſon'd in a Philoſophical Manner; ſhe found it good to put a New Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon him, being well aſſur'd, that that was the way to take him in the moſt ſenſible part, and that by this Method, ſhe ſhould always keep her Station with his Majeſty; for we are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily thankful, to thoſe who procure us ſuch things, as we believe to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for us. Our Marchioneſs then, to divert that Prince, brought to him at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> the moſt Beautiful Damſel of the World; but you will pardon me, if I don't tell you her Name, becauſe 'tis a Court Intrigue, which we keep very ſecret for Madam <hi>Maintenons</hi> ſake. 'Tis ſufficient, that ſhe is under her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in the Abbey of St. <hi>Cyr.</hi> Let's return to our fair Lady, who was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King, on purpoſe to Charm him, and to give the greateſt Mortification that could be to her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:60948:60"/>
            <p>His Majeſty, whoſe tenderneſs to the Sex is unlimited, and who Loves all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable Objects, took it very kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from our <hi>Heroeſs,</hi> and thankt her ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Joyfully, telling her, that he was indebted to her, for the moſt pleaſant Moments of his Life, and that having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt <hi>Madamoiſelle de Fontange</hi> that ſhe had alſo given him, and whom he che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſht alone, as an Adorable Perſon, and one Worthy to be Loved, This Lady might with Juſtice be ſaid to fill her place, and ſatisfie for the Loſs which he had ſuſtain'd, finding her every whit as Charming as ſhe was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam de Maintenon</hi> was extreamly glad, to find that her deſign had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo well, and that thereby, ſhe had rendred her ſelf always neceſſary for every thing that might tend to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Princes deſires, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought him acquainted with the Beauty of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> ſhe left our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Monarch with his New Chains, to ſatisfie himſelf at Leiſure, with the Pleaſures of his New Conqueſt.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:60948:61"/>
            <p>In the mean time, ſhe was taken up in her Ordinary Devotion, which was, to pray to God for the Soul of the Deceaſed <hi>Scarron,</hi> and <hi>Lent</hi> being at hand, ſhe went continually to St. <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to ſay her Prayers, with an almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Devotion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>La Caverne,</hi> one of her Maids, whom ſhe lov'd for her good Qualities, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture having Adorn'd her with a Wit proper for her purpoſe, accompanied her every where; and her Miſtreſs oftentimes entruſted her with her Secrets.</p>
            <p>One Day our Heroeſs acquainted her with the trouble ſhe endur'd, in Dreaming continually of <hi>Scarron</hi>'s Ghoſt; I confeſs to you my Dear, ſays ſhe, in a Mournful tone, that ſo long a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in Purgatory, is a ſevere Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Pleaſures which we may enjoy here in this World.</p>
            <p>For my part, Madam, replyed <hi>La Caverne,</hi> I believe Monſieur <hi>Scarron</hi> to be at reſt, and methinks that you have no further need of Praying to the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60948:61"/>Saints, and the Saints for Him: and this I obſerv'd when we were together in the Church of our <hi>Lady of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> for as you were upon your Knees before her, the good Mother of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeem'd to me to have heard your Prayers.</p>
            <p>Ah! my Dear, (cry'd the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) how cam'ſt thou to penetrate her Sacred Myſteries: thou muſt have ſurely had ſome ſecret Revelation from Heaven. I feel within my ſelf that Comfort which is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, from what thou haſt told me; and with all my Heart I beſeech that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Saint to afford me her Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance all the reſt of my Life.</p>
            <p>Never queſtion it in the leaſt, Madam, (reply'd <hi>La Caverne</hi> for ſhe is a good Conductreſs to Salvation, that liſtens to every word that is ſaid to her with a moſt Saint-like Affability, and works ſurprizing Miracles every day. One of my Couſins, (Madam) who had loſt her Sight with the <hi>Small-Pox,</hi> had no ſooner perform'd a Pilgrimage to this
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60948:62"/>ſame Queen of Heaven, but ſhe ſaw as well as I do: moreover, ſhe makes the Cooked Streight, and the Dumb to ſpeak, and does a hunder'd other things becoming her Grandeur.</p>
            <p>I was inform'd a long while ago of the moſt Admirable Vertues of this renown<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed Queen of Glory; for which reaſon I cannot do better then in addreſſing my Prayers for Mr. <hi>Scarron,</hi> to this <hi>Motion of Mercy,</hi> whoſe Goodneſs is ſo much to be admir'd. I aſſure thee, I have always had a particular Veneration for the Diſcretion and Civility of our <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Deliverance:</hi> as long as I live I ſhall always make her a Sacrifice of all the Affections of my Heart, my Vows and my Prayers: nay, I will make her privy to all my Sins and Tranſgreſſion for I am perſwaded ſhe will cleanſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> me with Hyſop, and pardon 'em all.</p>
            <p>What a Happineſs it is, (reply'd <hi>La Caverne</hi>) to find a Loving, General Saint, that will pardon us our Sins; for I find, (Madam) that you and I wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and go aſtray every hour of the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60948:62"/>Day, as Father <hi>Commire</hi> ſaid in his Pulpit laſt <hi>Sunday.</hi> And therefore it behooves us to pray to her, That ſhe would be pleas'd to let her ſweet Fac'd Angels continually accompany'd us.</p>
            <p>There would have been no end of this Superſtitious Jargonry between the Marchioneſs and her Secretary, but that ſhe was to ſend her to <hi>Paris</hi> to buy ſomething that was plain and modeſt for her to wear all the <hi>Lent;</hi> for that ſhe reſolv'd to haunt the <hi>Capuchin</hi>'s Church in the Dreſs of a Penitent. The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting of which Secret to the King, gave him as great a Satisfaction, as if his Minioneſs had made him a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of a Gold Mine. Nor did his Majeſty make any Body privy to it, but the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and that too under Enigmatical Expreſſions, telling him, That he had a Dream which had ſo vehemently charm'd him, that 'twas impoſſible for any man to expreſs in words the Pleaſure he found in it.</p>
            <p>Oh—Sir, (ſaid the Marſhal) of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity theſe muſt be ſome Sweets of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60948:63"/>Love that have infus'd into your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty this charming Enthuſiaſm. For I know nothing in the world that more delightfully invades our Sences then Amorou; Reflections. Moreover, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd the Marſhal) I know that you are never offended to ſee your ſelf willingly drill'd along by that inevitable Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to which we are reduc'd by the powerful Attractions of Beauty that ſo ſtrongly faſcinate us ſometimes, that we are no way able to defend our ſelves againſt 'em.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, (anſwer'd our Monarch) that the Great Pleaſure of my thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Meditations, was to ſee my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of the Perſon moſt deſerving A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration in the world: but my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs appear'd ſo great, that it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd my Knowledge. I could have wiſh'd with all my Soul, that the Dream had been real, but Felicities ſo real are ſeldom to be met with.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, (reply'd the Marſhal) a Prince that carries a thouſand Charms about him as you do, never ſighs long,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60948:63"/>as being aſſur'd of his Conqueſt. You are like <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you do but ſee and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh. I'le ſwear it upon all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that you are paſſionately belov'd when er'e you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>In good ſooth, (ſaid the King to the Marſhal) if all Womens Hearts were as tender as yours, We might affirm our ſelves happy. But I know ſome that are not ſo eaſily ſubdu'd. A man muſt take an incredible deal of Pain; about 'em, and yet they continue cruel to the end.</p>
            <p>I know very well, (reply'd the Marſhall) that a Woman's Merit is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerviceable to her, toward the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of her haughty Humour: but ſo ſoon as they begin to love us, that Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty ceaſes by degrees; and then a Man may eaſily perceive that Love which they take ſo much care to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal upon the ſcore of Modeſty: and generally 'tis that ſame Modeſty that charms me moſt: the more Reſerv'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I find in Virgin; or marry'd
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60948:64"/>Women, 'tis all one to me, the more eager am I in my purſuit.</p>
            <p>All Men (anſwer'd the King) are of the ſame Opinion: no body loves an eaſie Victory: the Pleaſure conſiſts in the Pains, and Reſiſtance increaſes it, if it be not carry'd on too far. Painters therefore are in the Right to ſhew us Enjoyment attended by a Tomb, to let us underſtand by that Emblem the Death of our Paſſions.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, (reply'd the Marſhal) 'tis ſeen that we continually aſpire to what we have not; and when we have it, our Joy deceaſes in the Poſſeſſion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis better to enjoy the Felicities of Life in Imagination, then loſe 'em in the Taſte of Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>That which cauſes this unequal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in us, (anſwer'd our Monarch) proceeds not from our ſelves. Nature is the Occaſion of all theſe Changeable Motions, with a deſign to inform us, that the Creatour is only conſtant and unvariable.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:60948:64"/>
            <p>But then Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> whoſe Entrance alter'd the Scene of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal's diſcourſe, appearing, ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal to her with a Smile, I thank my good Fortune that has afforded me the Honour of your good Company, which I never could yet enjoy, ſince I return'd from the Army.</p>
            <p>To tell you the Truth, Sir, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd the Marchioneſs) I have been for ſome time taken up with a world of Buſineſs; beſide that, I was forc'd to undertake a long Journey of above twenty Leagues from <hi>Paris,</hi> greatly to my ſorrow; for I do not love to be abſent from the Court: beſides that I am continually ſlav'd and turmoil'd with looking after my Young Fry at Saint <hi>Cyr.</hi>'s</p>
            <p>'Tis very true, Madam, that your Eminent Piety and Vertues are very rare in our Age; for, methinks, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion is at a very low Ebb. Any other Perſon but You would endeavour to make the beſt of ſo fair an Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60948:65"/>being the Darling of ſo Great a Prince as you are; 'tis a wonder to ſee you place your Felicity in ſuch Noble and Sublime Employments.</p>
            <p>But the King, who was deſirous to improve that little time the Marſhal had to ſpend in Winter-Quarters, fell into a long Conference with him concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Strength of the Enemy, and other Important Affairs of the War. Which being at an End, the King told him, That he intended to treat him with a Splendid Banquet and a Ball.</p>
            <p>The next day, his Majeſty gave Order to Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> to take Order for a Magnificent Banquet, and a Jolly Ball, to which ſeveral Princes and Princeſſes were invited, and where all the Ladies of the Court ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in the moſt pleaſant diſguizes in the World: and the Queen of <hi>England</hi> was the Goddeſs of that Charming Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
            <p>The King, whoſe thoughts were all entangl'd in his new Chains, carry'd
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60948:65"/>himſelf with an Extraordinary Gaity toward that Princeſs; he never ſtirr'd from her all the while the Ball laſted, making a thouſand Courtly Addreſſes to her, to which the Queen gave all along moſt engaging Anſwers: So that a man would then have thought ſhe had forgot all thoſe Fears, which the Jealouſie of her Rival had infus'd into her.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, our Heroeſs, who was at her Wits end to hear all thoſe Expreſſions that paſt between our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch and the Queen, durſt not for her Ears diſplay her reſentment; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condeſcended to ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placencies, which the King took mighty obligingly at her hands.</p>
            <p>'Tis the uſual Humour of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs to favour and forward all the King's Amours: On the Other ſide, ſhe procures all the Lovely Morſels ſhe can meet with, to feed his Pleaſures by the By, a ſort of Afternoons Lunche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Love; as being aſſur'd that 'tis the Only way to keep Poſſeſſion of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60948:66"/>his Heart: but ſhe cannot endure that his Majeſty ſhould make the Choice himſelf. And this is that which has lain heavy ſo long upon her Stomach, to ſee the King have ſuch an Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the baniſh'd Queen. The King alſo, who wants no Wit, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her Jealouſie, takes great delight, in his turn, to fret and diſcompoſe our Heroeſs, by careſſing the Queen, ſome times, with a greater Paſſion then ever he ſhew'd to his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The Day was ſpent in the uſual Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Eating and Drinking; and now the Night being come, they fell to Dancing helter-skelter. But as for Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> ſhe was always reſerv'd in all her Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements; and it may be ſaid of her, That ſhe made good the godly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which ſhe had acquir'd. You ſhall never ſee her blither nor more jocund at one time then another and this Equality of Temper gains her the Eſteem of all that ſee her; and for theſe Eminent Qualities it was that the King deem'd her worthy of his
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60948:66"/>Affections. But Marſhal <hi>de Luxemburgh,</hi> who had taken notice of the Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which the King had for the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> being deſirous to aſſiſt him in his Inclinations, took her out to dance ſeveral times; and in regard ſhe carries her ſelf with a moſt charming Air in Dancing, our Monarch ſignify'd his Acknowledgment to the Marſhal, by telling him, That there was no Sight ſo amiable, as to ſee two handſom Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons dance together.</p>
            <p>To whom the Marſhal reply'd, That if there were any thing of Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and Eminent in him, he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding firſt to the Queen's more Orient Luſtre, the Rays of which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected only upon Him; and that it was a uſual thing for the Sun to ſhed down his Beams upon every Thing in this World, and conferr Ornament up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Things the moſt deformed.</p>
            <p>This was look'd upon as a notable Complement for a Soldier, who has not time to ſtudy ſoft Addreſſes to La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60948:67"/>
            <p>The next day, the King remain'd all day long with the fair Queen of the Seraglio, where he diſplay'd the Exceſs of that Paſſion which he felt for her; aſſuring her a thouſand times of his Conſtancy, and the Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Love, and that he would never ſo much as ſeek after another change, as having never met ſo lovely a Perſon, and one ſo worthy of Royal Affection.</p>
            <p>Nor was our Prince, who found his Happineſs ſo great, content to load his charming Minioneſs with tender Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations; he put it home to her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, When he ſhould be ſo happy as to be belov'd by a Perſon ſo much deſerving Adoration as ſhe?</p>
            <p>To whom the lovely Queen, with an Air of perfect Modeſty, Sir, (ſaid ſhe) though you had neither Scepter nor Crown to embrighten the Luſtre of your Perſon; yet all your Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concurring with ſo much Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Accompliſhment, 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60948:67"/>that you ſhould be put to the Recoil where-e're you attempted Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. 'Twould be a Crime in Love, to permit a Hero, like your ſelf, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Foil in his Amours.</p>
            <p>Charm'd with ſo much Wit and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for his Miſtreſs, he teſtify'd his Acknowledgment in ſo paſſionate a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that nothing but the Vehemency of his Love could have ſupply'd him with the Vehemency of Expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who then lay at her Abbey, buſily taken up with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Care, expected the Queen's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; who gave her a faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the King's Love. On the other ſide, ſhe begg'd her Counſel what Courſe to take for the good Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this fortunate Beginning. The generous Abbeſs told her, That all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon the Firſt Movements, and that no body but ſhe alone could ſecure her an advantageous Succeſs: That her Experience had infus'd into her a little Knowledge in theſe Affairs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when ſhe was alone with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60948:68"/>at the ſame time ſhe ſtudy'd all manner of Ways to accompany her Words with a diſcreet and modeſt Air; a little Haughtineſs (continu'd our Heroeſs) intermix'd with Softneſs, if it be well manag'd, produces no bad Effect; for ſeveral young Ladies have loſt their Fortune, by rendring the Victory too eaſie. Mademoiſelle <hi>de Lude</hi> may ſerve yee for an Example, whoſe good Fortune prov'd ſo ſhort, that one Day began it, and the next concluded it: her too much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion ſpoil'd all; ſhe made too much haſte to be happy, and became unfortunate in a moment. Theſe were the admirable Inſtructions which Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> gave her Illuſtrious Scholar.</p>
            <p>But Madam <hi>de Villeroi,</hi> who had been ſeverely reprimanded by Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> was under a moſt mortal Affliction, to ſee her ſelf ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly look'd upon by that Lady. The important Occaſion of the Quarrel that had ſo warmly chaf'd the pious Marchioneſs's Choler, was this: Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60948:68"/>her Pilgrimage to our <hi>Lady of Deliverance,</hi> Mademoiſelle <hi>de Villeroi</hi> had taken a Walk with ſome of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, among whom were ſeveral Courtly Gentlemen, as the Chevalier <hi>Colbert,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Belfond,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Cheuvreuſe,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Buſſi;</hi> and ſhe had been a little too profuſe in her Expences upon 'em. Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> was no ſooner return'd from her Pilgrimage, but ſhe was inform'd of Madam <hi>de Villeroi</hi>'s Adventure. Upon which, ſhe rated her with all the Rigour and Severity imaginable; ſhe ſpar'd for no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches the moſt tart and cutting; telling her, ſhe would never ſee her more; That ſhe would baniſh her for ever from the bleſſed Aſſembly, where her good Fortune had enroll'd her; That the Habit ſhe wore ought to have put her in mind that ſhe was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon diſtinguiſh'd from the Common ſort of young Damſels in the World; and that by meeting Young Men abroad at publick Houſes of Entertainment, ſhe herded her ſelf with the Goſſips of the Town, that met their Gallants
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60948:69"/>above half way. Did you but know (continu'd our Heroeſs to the fair Damſel) how dangerous it is for a young Maiden to hearken to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Language of ſuch <hi>Enamorato's,</hi> eſpecially Soldiers, who talk at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom a thouſand things more then they think, and who have no ſooner made the Heart of a young Virgin flexible to Love, but they are preſently ſeeking out for another Booty, you would never truſt that inconſtant and wavering Sex, who thinks their Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſts in roving from one fair Lady to another, and never ſpeak ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely. You ſee how Painters ſet forth Love with Wings at his Back, to ſhew the Lightneſs and little Conſideration of that Paſſion. It becomes a modeſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſtick cloſe to her Needle; to ſpend her Time in Prayers and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to God, and his Holy Saints; and to endeavour to imitate Them, as the Divine Patterns of her Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. 'Tis alſo very neceſſary that young Maids ſhould read and ſtudy the Life of one of St. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Diſciples, where you find that that ſame holy Martyr
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60948:69"/>having had the Misfortune to feel in his Heart a petty Scuffle between the Fleſh and the Spirit, flung himſelf into a Bath of Water ſo cold, that it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently mortify'd all the criminal Deſires of rebellious Nature. Do you believe, that if the King knew you were a <hi>Coquet,</hi> he'd ever permit yee to live at St. <hi>Cyr</hi>'s? Never deceive your ſelf,—he's too Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a Prince to encourage Libertiniſm. The Marchioneſs was juſt concluding her Morality with ſeveral ſevere Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, <hi>If ever,</hi> &amp;c. when Marſhal <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> arriv'd to the ſeaſonable Relief of the poor diſconſolate Mademoiſelle <hi>de Villeroi,</hi> who was preſently diſpatch'd away to pray for more Diſcretion for the future. On the other ſide, Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who ſtill retain'd that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in her Eyes which her holy Zeal had kindl'd in her Countenance, receiv'd the Duke but very coldly: who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon demanded the Cauſe of her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure? Oh,— Sir, (cry'd the Marchioneſs, if you knew the Trouble that theſe giddy-brain'd Girls put me to, you would never wonder at it: I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to give 'em good Education,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60948:70"/>and ſet 'em an Example of Prudence and Piety; but the idle Baggages are ſo given to Romances and Love-Stories, ſo carry'd away with Coquettry, and other conſiderable Miſcarriages, that I have much ado to rule 'em; and this has put me into an ill Humour.</p>
            <p>Madam, (reply'd the Marſhal) you muſt conſider the Ladie; are Young, and Youth is apt to go aſtray; but riper Years, and your ſublime Inſtructions, will make thoſe deep Impreſſions in their Hearts, that there is no queſtion but you will reap the expected Fruit of your glorious Labours.</p>
            <p>What you ſay, Sir, (reply'd our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Heroeſs) is very obliging; but there is a neceſſity of correcting the Vices of Nature, and to make it our buſineſs to infuſe Vertue betimes. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World ſo praiſe-worthy in young Maidens, as Diſcretion and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty; which are the Principles by which they ought to act, and which only can aſſure 'em Happineſs both in this and the other Life.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:60948:70"/>
            <p>'Tis true, Madam, when Nature has made us a Preſent of theſe Noble Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, 'tis a glorious thing to improve 'em, ſo that they may be the prevailing Vertues triumphing in our Hearts.</p>
            <p>Sir, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I would entertain yee further upon this Subject, but that I hear my Nephew, the Abbot <hi>d'Aubigné,</hi> entring in, who will certainly alter the Scene of our Diſcourſe</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60948:71"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet:</hi> And <hi>J. Harris,</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Great Hiſtorical, Geographical, and Poetical Dictionary:</hi> Being a Curious Miſcellany of Sacred and Profane Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> collected out of the beſt Hiſtorians, Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, and Lexicographers; but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially out of <hi>Morery</hi>'s Sixth Edition, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and Enlarg'd by <hi>Le Clerke</hi> By ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Learned Men. To which are added the laſt Five Years Hiſtorical and Geographical Collections of <hi>Edmund Bohun,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The General Hiſtory of Europe,</hi> contain'd in the Hiſtorical and Political Monthly Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, from the late happy Revolution in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 1688. to this preſent Time. Giving an Account of all the Publick and Private Occurrences, Civil, Eccleſiaſtical and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,
<pb facs="tcp:60948:71"/>that are moſt Conſiderable in every Court: The Intereſt of Princes, their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and Intrigues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and generally all that is Curious. With Political Reflections upon every State. Done from the Originals, publiſh'd at the <hi>Hague</hi> by the Authority of the States of <hi>Holland.</hi> In Four Volumes: With an Index to each Volume.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Memoirs for the Ingenious:</hi> Containing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Curious Obſervations in Theology, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Mathematicks, Phyſick, Hiſtory, Philology, and other Arts and Sciences. In Miſcellaneous Letters to ſeveral of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops and Clergy, Eminent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Fellows of the Royal Society, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Year 1693. Bound up in one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. With a large Alphabetical Table to the Whole. By <hi>J. de la Croſe,</hi> Eccleſ. Angl. Presb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Triumph-Royal:</hi> Containing a ſhort Account of the moſt Remarkable Battels, Sieges, Sea-Fights, Treaties, and Famous Atchievements of the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Naſſan,</hi> &amp;c. Deſcrib'd in the Triumphal Arches, Pyramids, Pictures, Inſcriptions, and Devices, erected at the <hi>Hague</hi> in Honour of <hi>William</hi> III. King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Curiouſly Engraven in 62 Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures on Copper-Plates, with their Hiſtories; an Elaborate Piece of Curioſity. Firſt done
<pb facs="tcp:60948:72"/>in Dutch, then into French, and now into Engliſh. Dedicated to Her Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Preſent Court of Spain.</hi> Or, The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Gallantry of the Spaniſh Nobility un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded: In ſeveral Hiſtories, and Seventy five Letters from the Enamour'd <hi>Tereſa,</hi> to her Beloved the Marquis of <hi>Manſcra.</hi> By the Ingenious Lady — Author of <hi>The Memoirs and Travels into Spain.</hi> Done into Engliſh by <hi>J. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Voyages and Travels over Europe.</hi> Vol. I. Containing the Curioſities of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Volume of the Hiſtorical Voyages and Travels:</hi> Containing all that is moſt Curious in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Antidote against a Careleſs Indifferency in Matters of Religion.</hi> Being a Treatiſe in Oppoſition to thoſe that believe that all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions are Indifferent, and that it imports not what Men profeſs. Wherein the vulgar Objections of Atheiſts, Scepticks, Libertines, Latitudinarians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are briefly Anſwer'd. Done out of French. With an Introduction, by <hi>Anthony Horneck,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Preſent Condition of France,</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to her Revenues, comparing them
<pb facs="tcp:60948:72"/>with the infinite Expences ſhe is forc'd to be at. Demonſtrating thereby, That it is impoſſible for her to ſupport her ſelf, if the War with the Confederates continues. Done out of French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Paris Relation of the Battel of Landen,</hi> July 29th. 1693. between the French, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the D. of <hi>Luxemburgh;</hi> and the Confederates, by the K. of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> publiſh'd by the French King's Authority: With his Letter, ordering the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> to ſing <hi>Te Deum.</hi> And a Private Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from a very good Hand in <hi>Paris,</hi> with another Account of the Battel. As alſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon the King's Letter, by a very Learned French Pen. And Obſervations by another Hand here, proving the French King and his Gazetteers Account to be inconſiſtent with themſelves, and one another, as well as contrary to Truth: And that though the French kept the Field, yet they were really Loſers by the Action. Publiſh'd for Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Publick, who are ſo much Abus'd by Seditious Relations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Exact Relation of the Battel of Landen,</hi> July 29. 1693. between the Army of the Confederates, Commanded by the King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> and that of the French King, under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> With his Majeſty's Letter to the
<pb facs="tcp:60948:73"/>States o0f <hi>Holland,</hi> from his Head-Quarters at <hi>Eppegem,</hi> Aug. 12. 1693. With a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Order and Embattelling of both Armies at the Beginning of the Fight, in a Copper-Plate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60948:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
